贝蒂.戴维丝
安妮.柏丝特
乔治.桑托斯
西莉丝.特荷姆
慧星美人
[制片] 达利.桑尼克
编剧兼导演 约瑟夫.孟基维兹
或许你对莎拉.西顿杰出成就奖并不熟悉
The Sarah Siddons Award is perhaps unknown to you
它是用来颁给那些具知名度
It has been spared the sensational publicity
且最有价值的演员
of such questionable honors as the Pulitzer Prize
每年都由影艺协会来颁发
and those awards presented annually by that film society
这几位都是老牌演员
The distinguished-looking gentleman is an extremely old actor
由于身为演员 恐怕要讲上一阵子
Being an actor, he will go on speaking for some time
所讲的虽不十分重要
It is not important that you hear what he says
不过听听你是身在何处 或为何来此,是蛮重要的
However, it is important that you know where you are and why you are here
这里是莎拉奖的用餐大厅
This is the dining hall of the Sarah Siddons Society
正进行着杰出艺人表扬餐会
It is the annual banquet and presentation of the highest honor our theatre has:
莎拉杰出成就奖
the Sarah Siddons Award for Distinguished Achievement
在这些神圣的墙上
These hallowed walls, indeed many of these faces,
这些面孔都在注视着
have looked upon Modjeska, Ada Rehan and Minnie Fiske
这庄严的会场 屋里只有男人的声音
Mansfield's voice filled this room
跟死后成就才获肯定截然不同
It is unlikely that the windows have been opened since his death
如同你看到的那些较小奖项 都被颁发了
The minor awards, as you can see, have already been presented
例如编剧,导演奖
Minor awards are for such as the writer and director,
由于他们的成就有如建筑
since they merely construct a tower
架构出让世人喝采的美丽建筑
so that the world can applaud a light which flashes on top of it
可是再出风头也没有像 伊芙.哈林顿这般耀眼
And no brighter light has ever dazzled the eye than Eve Harrington
伊芙,但待会还有更多
Eve But more of Eve later
有关伊芙的事要告诉各位
All about Eve, in fact
有关伊芙及致谢词
To those who do not read,
对你们这些从未接触过戏剧 或上过剧院
attend the theatre, listen to unsponsored radio programs
或只听那无关紧要的电台节目 且对周遭世事不通的人
or know anything of the world in which you live,
或许我该自我介绍一下
it is perhaps necessary to introduce myself
我叫艾德生 杜维特
My name is Addison DeWitt
我的工作地点并非戏院 我也不出面讲话
My native habitat is the theatre In it, I toil not Neither do I spin
我是个影评人
I am a critic and commentator
也是戏剧的根本
I am essential to the theatre
这是凯伦.瑞奇
This is Karen Richards
是一位编剧的妻子 是经由婚姻才与戏剧结缘
She is the wife of a playwright, therefore of the theatre by marriage
以她背景本来是不该和 舞台扯上任何关系的
Nothing in her background should have brought her closer to the stage
然而在她念高中时
However, during her senior year at Radcliffe,
瑞奇先生的原著搬上银幕
Lloyd Richards lectured on the drama
来年凯伦便成为瑞奇太太
The following year Karen became Mrs Lloyd Richards
一般来说电影制片人分为两种
There are, in general, two types of theatrical producers
第一种制作人他有很多有钱朋友 愿意冒险来投资
One has a great many wealthy friends who will risk a tax-deductible loss
这种人是沉醉于艺术
This type is interested in art
而另一种制片人 每一部片子对他们而言
The other is one to whom each production means potential ruin or fortune
不是赔钱就是赚钱 这种人纯粹是想赚钱
This type is out to make a buck
麦斯.法宾先生
Meet Max Fabian
He is the producer of the play
他是制片人,为伊芙制作 一部夺得莎拉奖的戏剧
which has won for Eve Harrington the Sarah Siddons Award
玛歌.嘉琳是位戏剧明星
Margo Channing is a star of the theatre
在四岁时便登台演出
She made her first stage appearance at the age of four
“仲夏夜之梦”
in Midsummer Night's Dream
扮演一位仙女,完全令人意外 表现就如天生的明星
She played a fairy and entered, quite unexpectedly, stark naked
从那时起她便成为一位明星
She has been a star ever since
玛歌是一位伟大的明星
Margo is a great star A true star
一位真正的明星
She never was or will be anything less or anything else
她与众不同,十分杰出 并且空前绝后
Having covered in tedious detail not only the history of the Sarah Siddons Society,
赋予单调以色彩 不仅是莎拉影协的特色
but also the history of acting
也是表演界长久以来 固有的传统
since Thespis first stepped out of the chorus line,
贵宾终于开始谈到我们 为何来此的目的
our distinguished chairman has finally arrived at our reason for being here
我相当骄傲的,并光荣的将我的一生献给戏剧
I have been proud and privileged to have spent my life in the theatre,
一位穷苦的演员将自己的品味及风格 呈现在舞台上
a poor player that struts and frets his hour upon the stage,
我很荣幸能在舞台上 渡过四十年
and I've been honored to be, for 40 years,
是“舞台”激励了 我们莎拉影协会
chief prompter of the Sarah Siddons Society
在我39次亲自颁发
39 times have I placed in deserving hands
我们演艺圈最高荣誉莎拉奖
this highest honor the theatre knows
当然没有一个演员比我更老
Surely no actor is older than I
而这位子让我十分荣幸
I've earned my place out of the sun
这座奖从来没有落在 比今晚得主更年轻的人
And never before has this award gone to anyone younger than its recipient tonight
从我手中传到她手上 是再恰当也不过了
How fitting that it should pass from my hands to hers
如此年轻的手,如此年轻的女孩
Such young hands Such a young lady
岁数虽小,但对戏剧的心 却远超过陈旧的剧场
Young in years, but whose heart is as old as the theatre
我们在座其中有幸认识她
Some of us are privileged to know her
你们都知道她的美貌及演技 响誉国际
We have seen beyond the beauty and artistry
我们都知道她的谦逊
that have made her name resound through the nation
她的敬业精神 以及对艺术的忠诚
We know her humility, her devotion,
她的爱,她那诚挚专一的爱
her loyalty to her art,
为我们工作岗位上
her love, her deep and abiding love for us,
以及我们所做的事:戏剧
for what we are and what we do, the theatre
她曾经只有个愿望
She has had one wish,
有个祈求,一个梦想
one prayer, one dream,
成为我们的一分子
to belong to us
今晚她的梦想成真了
Tonight her dream has come true,
因此,我们也该和她 怀有同样的梦想
and henceforth we shall dream the same of her
各位贵宾,先生和女士们:戏剧界的最高荣誉
Ladies and gentlemen, for distinguished achievement in the theatre,
莎拉奖颁给伊芙.哈林顿小姐
the Sarah Siddons Award to Miss Eve Harrington
太棒了
So greatful
伊芙,黄金女郎 封面女郎
(Addison) Eve Eve, the golden girl The cover girl
像邻家般的女孩 如月亮上的嫦娥
The girl next door, the girl on the moon Time has been good to Eve
造化待她不薄 好运总跟随着她,做过人物专访,封面人物
Life goes where she goes She's been profiled, covered, revealed, reported,
影界资讯报导她 吃什么,穿什么
what she eats and what she wears and whom she knows
认识些什么人,现身在何处 或何时要跟谁去什么地方
and where she was and when and where she's going
伊芙,
Eve
你们对伊芙的事 都很了解
You all know all about Eve
但你不知道什么呢?
What can there be to know that you don't know?
那是什么时候呢? 那是多久以前?
(Karen) When was it? How long?
似乎是一辈子前的事
It seems a lifetime ago
罗维常说演艺圈的生活
Lloyd always said that in the theatre a lifetime was a season
就好比是季节一般
and a season a lifetime
现在是六月了 那是十月上旬的事
It's June now That was early October
只不过是去年的十月
Only last October
那是个下毛毛雨的夜晚 我记得叫计程车等我
It was a drizzly night I remember I asked the taxi to wait
她那时人在哪呢?
Where was she?
奇怪地每晚都去探望她 突然变成我的习惯
Strange I'd become so accustomed to seeing her there night after night,
我发觉自己在找寻一位
I found myself looking for a girl I'd never spoken to
从未说过话的女孩
Wondering where she was
瑞奇女士
Mrs Richards?
你在这里呀!
There you are
现在已经很晚了 你不该在这里的
It seemed odd, suddenly, your not being here
那到底怎样才恰当呢?天呀!难道你应该吗?
-Why should you think I wouldn't be? -Why should you be?
毕竟一连好几礼拜六个晚上
Six nights a week for weeks
来看玛歌.嘉琳进出剧院
of watching even Margo Channing enter and leave a theatre
-希望你不介意我跟你说话 -没关系
-You don't mind my speaking to you? -Not at all
我经常看到你,我鼓足勇气
I've seen you so often It took every bit of courage I could raise
才敢和编剧的老婆说话?
To speak to just a playwright's wife?
那我和罗维也算名人吗?
I'm the lowest form of celebrity
你们是玛歌.嘉琳最好的朋友 你和你先生总是在她身边
You're Margo Channing's best friend You and your husband are always with her
以及还有辛普生先生,他是个什么样的人呢?
And Mr Sampson What's he like?
辛普生,他是个导演
Bill Sampson? He's a director
-他是一流的 -他跟你会有同感的
-He's the best -He'll agree with you
告诉我,在玛歌进出剧院时 你都在做什么?
Tell me What do you do in between the time Margo goes in and comes out?
就站在门口等吗?
Just huddle in that doorway and wait?
不!我进去看戏
Oh, no I see the play
你进去看戏 你看过她所有演出的戏剧吗?
You see the play? You've seen every performance of this play?
是的
Yes
但你不觉得
But don't you find it
这些花费太昂贵了吗?
Apart from everything else, don't you find it expensive?
站票不太贵,我还付得起
Standing room doesn't cost much I manage
-我带你去玛歌那里 -不行
-I'm gonna take you to Margo -Oh, no!
-行!她一定得见你 -不要 -在她面前我会不知所措
-Oh, yes She's got to meet you -No, I'd be imposing on her
我一定会讲不出话来
I'd be just another tongue-tied fan
再也找不到你这种人了 绝对不会
There isn't another like you There couldn't be
-下次好了,你看我这一身 -你看来很好呀!
If I'd known, Some other time. Looking like this
对了,你叫什么名字?
You look just fine By the way, what's your name?
伊芙.哈林顿
Eve Eve Harrington
瑞奇太太,你好
-Good evening, Gus -Good evening, Mrs Richards
-晚安! -晚安
-Good night -Good night, Gus
你可以闻到刺鼻的味道
You can breathe it, can't you?
如同神奇的香水般
Like some magic perfume
在这里等,别走开
Wait right here Don't run away
-嗨! -你好,音乐会如何?
"If the South had won, you could write plays about the North "
-柴先生,至少你能光明正大说
-Hi -Hello!
-我帮你倒杯喝的 -我不认为我们战败了
"I don't think you can rightly say we lost the war "
我们没得奖 是因为我们太先进了
"We was more starved out, you might say "
但我实在不明白,那些有关 南方女人的爱情故事
"I don't understand all these plays about love-starved Southern women "
只有对南方的爱,我们落伍了
"Love is one thing we were never starved for in the South "
玛歌接见一位南方的女记者
Margo's interview with a reporter from the South
只要这话一见报 他们又要从盖茨堡点燃战火
When it gets printed, they're gonna fire on Gettysburg again
再掀起一次南北战争 至少这是值得的 －我从不会为某种企图演戏
-It was Fort Sumter they fired on -I never played Fort Sumter
亲爱的罗维 做个有胆识的编剧
Honeychild had a point Lloyd, honey, be a playwright with guts
把我写成正常的好女人 而且只适合她的丈夫
Write me one about a nice, normal woman who just shoots her husband
-你不需要束腰吗? -去找一件
-You need new girdles -Buy some
-同样的尺寸? -当然
-Same size? -Of course
我越来越觉得 这些低级笑话并不好笑
I find these wisecracks increasingly less funny
-“林中岁月”的确是一部叫座的好戏 -这才是我罗维的女人
-Aged in Wood happens to be a fine play -That's my loyal little woman
影评人是这么认为 观众当然也是这么认为
The critics thought so The audiences think so
大家争相来看 票四个月前就卖光了
Packed houses, tickets four months in advance
我看不出罗维的戏 会带给你任何伤害
I can't see that Lloyd's plays have hurt you any
放松，放松，又没有别人.天知地知，我知你知.
-Easy now -Relax, kid, it's just me and my big mouth
有时你实在让我很生气
You get me so mad sometimes
全世界女人没什么好抱怨的
Of all the women with nothing to complain about
-这是真的吗? -是的,这是真的
-Ain't it the truth? -Yes, it is
你有天份,有名气,有钱
You're talented, famous, wealthy
人们日夜的等待 就为见你一面,即使是刮风下雨的日子
People waiting around night after night just to see you Even in the rain
看看那场面,他们还是人吗?
Autograph fiends They're not people
他们就像跑在大街上的土狼
Little beasts that run around in packs like coyotes
他们是你的朋友,你的观众 -他们才不是我的朋友
-They're your fans -They're nobody's fans
是不良少年,神经病 才不是我的观众
They're juvenile delinquents They're nobody's audience
他们从未看过戏或是电影 他们在室内绝对待不久
They never see a play or a movie They're never indoors long enough
现在门外就有个观众
Well, there's one indoors right now
我将她带来见你 什么?
-I've brought her back to see you -You've what?
她就在门外
She's just outside the door
叫她走
The heave-ho
你不能把她赶走,我答应过她
But you can't put her out I promised
玛歌你得见她
Margo, you've got to see her
她好祟拜你 就好比童话故事一样
She worships you It's like something out of a book
那种故事早绝版了,凯伦,那种时代早过了
That book is out of print Those days are gone
只要你见她一面 你是她人生的全部
But if you'd only see her You're her whole life
你一定见过她 她总是在那里呀!
You must have spotted her by now She's always there
那鬼鬼祟祟家伙穿件破大衣 戴顶可笑帽子
Oh, the mousy one with the trench coat and the funny hat
-她每晚都在,我怎会错过呢!
How could I miss her? Every night, every matinee
进来吧，伊芙
Come in, Eve
-我还以为你已经忘了我 -才不会呢!
-I thought you'd forgotten about me -Not at all
-玛歌,这是伊芙.哈林顿 -你好,亲爱的
Margo, this is Eve Harrington
-天呀! -你好!嘉琳小姐
-How do you do, my dear? -Oh, brother
-我先生 -哈林顿小姐,你好
-Hello, Miss Channing -My husband
你好,瑞奇先生
-Hello, Miss Harrington -How do you do?
这位是我好友及随伴 柏蒂库门小姐
And this is my dear friend and companion, Miss Birdie Coonan
-我的天呀!
-Oh, brother -Miss Coonan
-库门小姐,什么我的天?看她这个样子
-Oh, brother, what? -When she gets like this,
突然扮成慈母的模样
she starts playing Hamlet's mother
柏蒂,我相信你在浴室 还有事要做吧!这个可爱的柏蒂
I'm sure you must have things to do in the bathroom, Birdie, dear
如果我没有，我仍然能找到什么办法把你变回来
If I haven't, I'll find something till you get normal
威林顿小姐,你请坐呀!
Won't you sit down, Miss Worthington?
是哈林顿!-非常抱歉,哈林顿
Harrington
抱歉，坐下吗？谢谢.
-I'm so sorry Won't you sit down? -Thank you
-你要不要来点饮料？
Would you like a drink?
-一杯水？-我刚跟玛歌说你常去看她的戏
I was saying how often you've seen the play
不，谢谢.
No, thank you
是的,每场戏我都看过每一场戏?
Yes, I've seen every performance
那我猜你一定喜欢啰!
Every performance? Then am I safe in assuming you like it?
我喜欢嘉琳小姐 演出的每一场戏 你嘴巴真甜
-I'd like anything Miss Channing played in -Would you really? How sweet
我倒是很怀疑,你会喜欢 她那部“苦命女”?
I doubt very much that you'd like her in The Hairy Ape
瑞奇先生,请不要误解
Please don't misunderstand me, Mr Richards
我认为嘉琳小姐最伟大之处 在于她能依其所长 挑选出最好的戏来演
I think part of Miss Channing's greatness lies in her ability to pick the best plays
你新戏是为嘉琳小姐写的吧!
Your new play is for Miss Channing, isn't it?
那当然了
Of course it is
你是怎么听来的? 是时代杂志上说的
-How did you hear about it? -There was an item in The Times
我喜欢那个片名 “天花板上的足迹”
I like the title, Footsteps on the Ceiling
我们再回头谈谈
Yes, but let's get back to this one
你真的看过她每部戏吗? 是的!
-Have you really seen every performance? -Yes
为什么?我很好奇
Why? I'm curious
如果我不去看戏 我就没有别的地方好去
Well, if I didn't come to see the play, I wouldn't have anywhere else to go
总有别的戏呀!
There are other plays
那里可就没有你 也不是瑞奇先生编剧
Not with you in them Not by Mr Richards
但你总该有朋友或家庭吧!
But you must have friends, a home, family?
说说吧，伊芙
Tell us about it, Eve
-我不知该如何说起? -试试看嘛!
-If I only knew how -Try
这样
-Well -(door opens)
-事情是从上场戏开始 -“回忆”（片名）
Well, it started with the play before this one
“回忆”
-Remembrance -Remembrance
你是在这里,还是纽约看的? 在旧金山看的
-Did you see it here in New York? -San Francisco
在上星期一个晚上去看的
It was the last week I went one night
那是我一生最重要的一夜 直到现在
The most important night of my life, until now
我发觉我隔夜又去了 然后再隔夜,隔夜
I found myself going the next night and the next and the next
每场戏
Every performance
直到戏移到东部去演出 我也去了东部
Then, when the show went East, I went East
伊芙,你何不从头说起呢? -你们不会感兴趣的
-Eve, why don't you start at the beginning? -Oh, it couldn't possibly interest you
-请说吧!
Please
我想该从家乡说起 我是威斯康星州人
I guess it started back home Wisconsin, that is
家中有爸妈和我
It was just Mom and Dad and me
我是家里唯一的孩子
I was an only child
小时候时常去假扮很多东西
I used to make believe a lot when I was a kid
把各种东西都表演出来 这很重要吗?
Acted out all sorts of things What they were isn't important
总之,表演,假扮 越来越不能满足我
But, somehow, acting and make-believe began to fill up my life more and more
让我越来越不能分辨 什么是真,什么是假的
It got so I couldn't tell the real from the unreal
有时假的让我觉得更像真的.
Except that the unreal seemed more real to me
我好像在胡言乱语了,是吧? 一点也不
-I'm talking a lot of gibberish, aren't I? -Not at all
那时的农人都很穷 父亲也是如此,他是个农夫
Farmers were poor in those days That's what Dad was, a farmer
我很讨厌农事
I had to help out
所以就休学 去密尔瓦基做秘书 在布威尔酒厂
So I quit school, went to Milwaukee, became a secretary in a brewery
在布威尔做秘书时,要假扮任何东西都很难
When you're a secretary in a brewery, it's hard to make believe you're anything else
什么事都跟啤酒有关
Everything is beer
并不是有趣的工作 不过倒是能贴补家用
It wasn't much fun, but it helped at home
就像是沙漠中的一滴甘露
And there was a little theatre group there, like a drop of rain on the desert
也因此我认识了艾迪
That's where I met Eddie
他是个无线电技工
He was a radio technician
我们演出过三场戏
We played Liliom for three performances
那时演得好糟
I was awful
然后大战来了,我们结了婚
Then the war came and we got married
艾迪投效了空军
Eddie was in the air force
他们派他去南太平洋
They sent him to the South Pacific
瑞奇先生,你也在OWI是吗?
You were with the OWI, weren't you, Mr Richards?
这是那个什么来着说的
That's what Who's Who says
他便是派到这支巡逻队 等爸死后,我又回到这里生活
Well, with Eddie gone, my life went back to beer
就除了每周收到他的信
Except for a letter a week
有一周他写信告诉我 他快休假了
One week he wrote me he had leave coming up
我就存点钱,积些假期 到旧金山去见他
I'd saved my money and vacation time and went to San Francisco to meet him
但艾迪却不在那里
But Eddie wasn't there
他们转来一封发自 密尔瓦基的电报
They forwarded the telegram from Milwaukee
原本来自华盛顿的电报
The one that came from Washington
上面说艾迪再也不能来了,
To say that Eddie wasn't coming at all
艾迪死了
That Eddie was dead
当时我想留在旧金山算了
I figured I'd stay in San Francisco
我孤零零一个人 没有艾迪我也回不去
I was alone I couldn't go back without Eddie
我找到一份工作 是一家保险公司
I found a job, and his insurance helped
而旧金山也有戏院
And there were theatres in San Francisco
然后有一晚,玛歌.嘉琳的 “回忆”在此上演了,
And then, one night, Margo Channing came to play in Remembrance,
我就去看戏
and I went to see it
嗯
Well
因此我就到这里来了
Here I am
真是感人的故事 如过街老鼠般
What a story Everything but the bloodhounds snapping at her rear end
这其中有着一些人生经历 不要用俗话来作批评
There are some human experiences that do not take place in a vaudeville house!
即使是那些念到五年级的人 也懂得尊敬别人的道理
And that even a fifth-rate vaudevillian should understand and respect
-我代柏蒂向你道歉 -你不必为我道歉
-I want to apologize for Birdie -You don't have to apologize for me
如果我伤了你的心 我很抱歉 我说话就是这个样子
I'm sorry if I hurt your feelings It's just my way of talking
库门太太,你没有
You didn't hurt my feelings, Miss Coonan
叫我柏蒂就行了
Call me Birdie
至于念到五年级
And as for being fifth-rate,
我念得比你知道的还多 我念到十一年级
I closed the first half for eleven years, and you know it
飞机已到了四十分钟 都还没准备好
47 minutes from now my plane takes off and how do I find you?
-看起来像是垃圾堆一样 -非常谢谢
-Not ready, looking like a junkyard -Thank you so much
这是怠工吗? 不把我的事业放在眼里吗?
Is it sabotage? Have you no human consideration?
-一点体谅的心都没有吗? -你说呢?我可能有的,飞机都守时的,你却没有
-Show me a human and I might have -Airlines have clocks, even if you don't
我从星期一起拍一礼拜的戏 杰妮卡她没耐性,她需要我
I start shooting a week from Monday Zanuck is impatient
杰妮卡,杰妮卡 你们两个是情侣吗?
Zanuck, Zanuck! What are you two? Lovers?
-在某方面你是比较漂亮 -我是垃圾堆吗?
-Only in some ways You're prettier -I'm a junkyard
-比尔导演,这位是伊芙.哈林顿 -你好
-Bill This is Eve Harrington -Hi
我美妙的垃圾堆,我梦中情人是在 垃圾堆中找到的
My wonderful junkyard The mystery and dreams you find in a junkyard
老天,快救我!
Heaven help me
我喜欢一个神经病
I love a psychotic
你好!你叫什么名字? 伊芙,伊芙.哈林顿
-Hello What's your name? -Eve Harrington
-你们早见过了 -在那里?
-You've already met -Huh? Where?
-就在这里,一分钟前 -那很好啊!
-Right here, just a minute ago -That's nice
你不是想走吧! 我想我最好都已经
-You're not going, are you? -I think I'd better
我实在是说不出来
It's been I can hardly find the words to say how it's been
不,别走
No, don't go
你们四人一定有好多话要说 关于辛普生要远行的事
The four of you must have so much to say to each other with Mr Sampson leaving
请留下来,告诉你原因
No, stick around, please
我们先安排史丹劳斯基的演出 你和我再找个地方谈谈
Tell you what We'll put Stanislavsky on his plane, then go somewhere and talk
-如果我不碍事的话
Well, if I'm not in the way
-不会的
I won't be a minute
-罗维,我们该走了 -是呀!
Lloyd, we've got to go
晚安!玛歌
Good night, Margo
-明天打电话给你 -别太早了
-I'll call you tomorrow -Not too early
-祝你好运,导演 -天才不需要好运的 而我需要
-Good luck, genius -Geniuses don't need good luck I do
-我不担心你 -保有这种想法
-I'm not worried about you -Keep the thought
晚安,伊芙 希望很快再见到你
Good night, Eve. I hope I see you again soon
-明天我还会站在那老地方 -不是以这种方式 而是以朋友的方式
-I'll be at the old stand tomorrow matinee -Not just that way As a friend
我喜欢这样
I'd like that
-你真是个令人愉快的人 -但愿如此,瑞奇先生 -晚安
-It's been a real pleasure, Eve -I hope so, Mr Richards Good night
晚安
Good night
瑞奇太太
Mrs Richards?
只要活着,
I'll never forget this night as long as I live
我永远不会忘记
And I'll never forget you for making it possible
我也永远不会忘记你,伊芙
(Karen) And I'll never forget you, Eve
那晚我和罗维去了哪里呢?
Where were we going that night, Lloyd and I?
真奇怪,该记住的事
Funny, the things you remember
反倒忘了
and the things you don't
因此你要去好莱坞吗?
-So you're going to Hollywood? -Mm-hm
-为何这么问? -我只是奇怪
-Why? -I just wondered
只是奇怪什么? 为什么呢?
-Just wondered what? -Why?
什么为什么? 为何你要离开到那里去?
-Why what? -Why you have to go out there
不是必须要,是我想要 为了钱吗?
-I don't have to I want to -Is it the money?
百分之八十都纳税走了
80% of it'll go for taxes
那是为了什么呢? 一位年轻杰出的戏剧导演 又为了什么?
Then why? Why, if you're the most successful young director in the theatre
戏剧,戏剧
The theatre The theatre
哪本书规定导演只能存在
What rules say the theatre exists only within some ugly buildings
纽约的方圆一哩内 挤在几间破旧的大楼里
crowded into one square mile of New York City?
应该到巴黎或维也纳
Or London, Paris or Vienna?
你听着,年轻人也想学习
Listen, Junior, and learn
你想知道戏剧是什么? 马戏团,歌剧也是
Do you wanna know what the theatre is? A flea circus Also opera
马术大赛也是 嘉年华会,芭蕾
Also rodeos, carnivals, ballets,
印地安人部落集会 单人乐队等,都是戏剧
Indian tribal dances, Punch and Judy, a one-man band, all theatre
只要能弄假成真的戏法 能有观众来看的都叫戏剧
Wherever there's magic and make-believe and an audience, there's theatre
唐老鸭,还有独行侠
Donald Duck, Ibsen and The Lone Ranger
莎拉 伯哈顿 幸运泉,贝蒂 葛莱宝
Sarah Bernhardt and Poodles Hanneford Lunt and Fontanne, Betty Grable
红老马,仙纳 杜雪 这都是戏剧
Rex the Wild Horse, Eleonora Duse, all theatre
你根本就不了解 你也不一定都喜欢
You don't understand them all You don't like them all
那你为何要看呢?
Why should you?
戏剧是属于大家的,也包括你 但不是专属于你个人
The theatre's for everybody, you included, but not exclusively
有些人欣赏,有些人反对
So, don't approve or disapprove
或许不是你要的戏剧 可是总是属于某人的戏剧
It may not be your theatre, but it's theatre for somebody, somewhere
我只问你一个简单的问题
I just asked a simple question
那我闭嘴好了
And I shot my mouth off
非专业的初学者没什么
Nothing personal, Junior No offense
只是太多中产阶级及外行人 他们所称的戏剧
It's just that there's so much bushwa in this ivory greenroom they call the theatre,
有时真该说他们两句
sometimes it gets up around my chin
但好莱坞,你要远离那里
But Hollywood You mustn't stay out there
-只不过拍一部影片 -所以你要回来
-It's only a one-picture deal -So few come back
我每周阅读乔治内幕报导
I read George Jean Nathan every week
-以及专家报导? -每天都看
-Also Addison DeWitt -Every day
这点不必跟我说
-You didn't have to tell me -(door opens)
我了解戴一只耳环是很懒散的
It's the latest thing, one earring
不过也没办法 我找不到另一只
If it isn't, it's going to be I can't find the other one
你又到处乱放了
Throw that dreary letter away It bores me
-那会放哪里去呢? -它一定会出现的
-Where do you suppose it could be? -It'll show up
我放弃了!走道上看看 或许你会捡到一个2毛5
Oh, I give up Look in the wigs Maybe it got caught in one
每个礼拜掉一颗真钻 我们过得真慷慨呀!
Real diamonds in a wig The world we live in
-我的大衣呢? -就在你脱衣服的地方
-Where's my coat? -Right where you left it
丝袜!
The seams
-他就目不转睛注视我双腿
He can't take his eyes off my legs
-如同贴身丝袜一样
Like a nylon lemon peel
就算拜伦也无法说得那么优雅
Byron couldn't have said it more graciously
好了!我们走吧!
Here we go
有什么话要说吗?
Got any messages?
要我向泰隆鲍华说些什么?
What do you want me to tell Tyrone Power?
只要给我他的电话号码 我会自己说的
Just give him my phone number I'll tell him myself
好好照顾他们
Kill the people
-你的锁匙拿了吧! -回家见!
-You got your key? -See you at home
我有个建议 时间不是不太够吗?
I have a suggestion There's really not very much time left
我是说你们好久不见了
I mean, you haven't had a minute alone yet
我可以照料这一切 待会在入口处碰面就行了
And I could take care of everything here and meet you at the gate with the ticket,
你们觉得怎么样?
if you'd like
-我们很乐意,
I think we'd like very much
-Sure you won't mind? -Of course not
真的不介意? -当然不会
她真是个伶巧的女孩 叫什么名字? 伊芙,我忘了他们 是那么长大的
-She's quite a girl, this whatshername -Eve I'd forgotten they grew that way
说真的 她倒是有一种天生的慧根
That lack of pretense, that strange directness and understanding
她是否跟你谈到戏剧? 你有何高见?
Did she tell you about the theatre and what it meant?
不,我跟她盖了一大堆
No, I told her I sounded off
天下万教殊途同归
All the religions in the world rolled into one,
而上帝还是上帝
and we're gods and goddesses
你说这好不好笑? 突然我有一种 想保护她的念头
Isn’t it silly? Suddenly I've developed a big, protective feeling toward her
她像只迷失在丛林的羔羊
A lamb loose in our big, stone jungle
你自己多保重 我明白他们有着 像印地安人的陷阱
-Take care of yourself out there -They have the Indians pretty well in hand
比尔,
Bill
别迷上那些狐狸精 我尽量
-Don't get stuck on some glamour puss -I'll try
跟她们打交道,你既粗心 又不会说话,斗不过她们的
You're not much of a bargain You're conceited, thoughtless and messy
-不是每个人都像格里高利.派克 -年轻貌美又狂野的女子 是你最想要的
-Everybody can't be Gregory Peck -You're a setup for some young babe
你怎么说这种孩子气的话
How childish are you gonna get before you stop it?
我才没有 这几年我早就定下心了
I don't wanna be childish I'd settle for a few years
那就别再说了
And cut that out right now
比尔,我会失去你吗? 我会吗?
Am I going to lose you, Bill? Am I?
-此刻你才六岁大而已
As of this moment, you're six years old
-已经好了
All ready
谢谢你的帮忙,祝你好运
Thanks for your help Good luck
再见!辛普森先生
Goodbye, Mr Sampson
-你会到马佛吗? -你到了以后打个电话给我
-Knit me a muffler? -Call me when you get in
年轻人
(Bill) Hey, Junior!
看着她点,别让她寂寞
Keep your eye on her Don't let her get lonely
她是只丛林里迷失的羔羊
She's a loose lamb in a jungle
别担心
Don't worry
就在那一晚 我们整理伊芙的东西
(Margo) That same night, we sent for Eve's things, her few pitiful possessions
她的日用品搬进顶楼那房间
She moved into the little guest room on the top floor
在接下来的三个礼拜中
The next three weeks were out of a fairy tale,
我就如同灰姑娘般 得到格外的礼遇
and I was Cinderella in the last act
伊芙变成我姐妹,律师,母亲 朋友,心理医生以及警察
Eve became my sister, lawyer, mother, friend, psychiatrist and cop
蜜月开始了
The honeymoon was on
-再来一次吗?
One more?
-要不是为了清场
From now on it isn't applause,
我都想躺到地板去了
just something to do till the aisles get cleared
什么，再来？
What, again?
看你最后一幕表演上千遍 但每次还是会哭
I could watch you play that last scene a thousand times, cry every time
这出戏从来没演过那么久
Performance number 1,000 of this one, if I play it that long,
这么做不被认为傻瓜才怪
will take place in a well-padded booby hatch
我要说你该告诉辛普森先生 他电话打了一个月了
I must say, you can certainly tell Mr Sampson's been gone a month
你当然可以这么说
You certainly can
明早之前他会再打电话给我
Especially if you're me between now and tomorrow morning
你买的新束腰太小了 我感觉得出来
You bought the new girdles a size smaller I can feel it
也许里面什么东西变大了
Something maybe grew a size larger
我看回家你来穿这束腰 试个两个半小时看会如何?
You can get into one of those girdles and act for two and a half hours
我花两个半小时 也穿不进这束腰的
I couldn't get into the girdle in two and a half hours
你没注意到我最近的新创意
You haven't noticed my latest bit of interior decorating
但你已经做了很多了 又有什么新创举?
(Margo) But you've done so much What's new?
窗帘,是我自己做的
The curtains I made them myself
它们很可爱-柏蒂,它们可爱吗?
They're lovely Aren't they lovely, Birdie?
-太可爱了
Adorable
现在所有东西都是手工做的 除了篮球架之外
We now got everything a dressing room needs except a basketball hoop
还不是因你连脱鞋都不会做
Just because you can't even work a zipper!
伊芙,你很有创意 我很欣赏
It was very thoughtful of you, Eve I appreciate it
趁你在卸妆,我把戏服 送去服装间
I'll just take this to the wardrobe mistress
-别麻烦,布朗太太会来拿
Don't bother Mrs Brown will be along soon
-一点也不麻烦
No trouble at all
我可大胆对你说些事吗?
May I be so bold as to say something?
你听过“工会”这个字吗? -照你的行情,那该多少?
-Have you ever heard of the word "union"? -Behind in your dues? How much?
-我没有工会,我是个奴隶
-I haven't got a union I'm slave labor -Well?
可是管服装的女人 可是加入了工会
But the wardrobe women have got one and, next to a tenor,
在演艺界最不能惹的 就是管服装的女人
a wardrobe woman is the touchiest thing in show business
她只做两件事 不是带走,就是摆错地方
She's got two things to do: carry clothes and press 'em wrong
千万别让人说闲话了
And don't let anybody try to muscle in
最好让布朗太太来收戏服
We'd better let Mrs Brown pick up the wardrobe
喂
(phone rings)Hello
我们已经帮你接通 比佛利山庄的电话了
We are ready with your call to Beverly Hills
什么电话? 这里是89970 玛歌.嘉琳住宅吗?
-Call? What call? -Is this Templeton 89970? Miss Channing?
是的,我了解了
Yes, it is, but I don't understand
我们准备替你转接加州 辛普森先生电话,
We are ready with the call you placed for 12 midnight, California time,
你愿付费吗
to Mr Sampson
-我付 -请说吧!
-I placed? -Go ahead, please
-玛歌,好棒的惊喜
(Bill) Margo, what a wonderful surprise
-玛歌,好棒的惊喜 -你真是体贴呀!
What a thoughtful, ever-lovin' thing to do
比尔,我是不是疯了?
Bill Have I gone crazy, Bill?
-你是我的乖女孩 -我是吗?
-You're my girl, aren't you? -That I am
那么你是疯了
Then you're crazy
你何时回来? 再一礼拜吧!
-When are you coming back? -I leave in a week
影片都拍好了 昨晚我们试片了
The picture's wrapped up We previewed last night
哦，哪些试片
Oh, those previews
那场试片在市郊公演 但还是很恐怖,一点办法也没有
Like opening out of town, but terrifying There's nothing you can do
都动弹不得,就像在锡罐中
You're trapped You're in a tin can
锡罐中?那么快脱身吧! 我要你回家来
In a tin can, cellophane or wrapped in a Navajo blanket, I want you home
要很快吗? 要很快,所以就快一点吧!
-You in a hurry? -In a big hurry, so be quick about it
再见,达令,好好睡哦!
Goodbye, darling Sleep tight
等等,不能挂呀! 我们还没说话耶!
Hey, wait a minute You haven't even said it yet
比尔,别现在嘛! 你知道我工作多累呀!
Oh, now, Bill You know how much I do, but over a phone
你真是的!真是孩子气
Now, really That's kids' stuff
我又不是天天这样 我只想听你讲话嘛!
Kids' stuff or not It doesn't happen every day and I wanna hear it
如果你不想说,我就用唱的 用唱的?
-And if you won't say it, you can sing it -Sing it?
当然,就像西城工会的人
Sure, like the Western Union boys used to do
比尔,
Bill
今天是你的生日
It's your birthday
你还记得吗? 总是在那半夜12点
And who remembered it? Who was there on the dot at 12 midnight?
生日快乐,达令
Happy birthday, darling
你可再说得好一点呀!
The reading could've been better, but you said it
所有的快乐都回归到这一天
Now, "Many happy returns of the day "
Many happy returns of the day
我会有个生日派对? 当然 生日,记得回家
-I get a party, don't I? -Of course Birthday and coming home
-我该请谁来? -那不是秘密,我知道 伊芙替我买了生日礼物
-Who will I ask? -I know all about the party Eve wrote me
她做的吗? 是的,一礼拜前我收到了
-She did? -She hasn't missed a week since I left
一周前你也许告诉她要写些什么了吧
But you know that You probably tell her what to write
反正我把派对名单寄给她了 你和她核对一下
I sent her a list of guests, so check with her
我会的!
Yeah, I will
-她好吗? -很好!
-How is Eve? OK? -OK
-我爱你 -我也会查的
-I love you -I'll check with Eve
-什么? -我也爱你!
I love you, too Good night, darling
晚安!
See ya
柏蒂
-Birdie -Hm?
你不喜欢伊芙,是吗?
You don't like Eve, do you?
你是要吵架,还是答案呢?
You want an argument or an answer?
-给我答案 -不喜欢!
-An answer -No
-为什么? -现在你想吵架
-Why not? -Now you want an argument
-她工作卖力 -日以继夜
-She works hard -Night and day
-她忠实又有效率 -就像只有一个客户的经纪人
-She's loyal and efficient -Like an agent with only one client
她只为我个人着想
She thinks only of me,
不是吗?
doesn't she?
我想她只为她自己着想
Well, let's say she thinks only about ya, anyway
你这话是怎么说? 我告诉你她如何?
-How do you mean that? -I'll tell ya how
就像
Like
就像她在研究你
Like she's studying you
就像在研究你的戏 做笔记,阅读你的书
Like you was a play, or a book, or a set of blueprints
研究你如何走路,讲话 吃东西,思考
How you walk, talk, eat, think
我确知这是很会拍马屁 但我不觉得有什么不对
I'm sure that's flattering There's nothing wrong with it
早安!
(knock on door)
你觉得我穿上你高雅衣服如何
Good morning Well, what do you think of my elegant new suit?
非常合身,比我穿要好看多了
It looks much better on you than it did on me
我实在无法相信 你知道我只要修改一下就行了
I can imagine All it needed was a little taking in here and letting out there
你确定真的不想穿吗?
Are you sure you won't want it yourself?
很肯定,我觉得这对我来说 太年轻了些
Quite sure I find it too seventeenish for me
得了,你又不是老女人
Come now, as though you were an old lady
我现在要去办事 你还想到有什么事吗?
I'm on my way Is there anything else?
-你把剧本送回去协会 -我拿了
-That script to take to the Guild -I've got it
-还有开出支票预付所得税
And those checks for the income-tax man
-我带了
Right here
看来我想到的事 你早就想到了
It seems I can't think of a thing you haven't thought of
那是我的工作 午茶时再见
That's my job See you at teatime
伊芙
Eve?
你是否曾代我打电话给比尔? 在加州的午夜时刻
Did you place a call from me to Bill for midnight California time?
老天!我竟然给忘了 -是的,你全忘了
-Golly, I forgot to tell you! -Yes, dear, you forgot all about it
当然,我知道你一定很想 在他生日那天打电话给他
I was sure you'd want to, being his birthday
这几天你一直都很忙,昨晚你和瑞奇先生外出时 我本想告诉你
You've been so busy lately Last night I meant to tell you before you went out
后来想等你回来再说 但是我睡着了
I guess I was asleep when you got home
我信得过你,你做事很细心
Yes, I guess you were It was very thoughtful of you, Eve
辛普森先生的生日 我怎能忘记呢?
Mr Sampson's birthday, I couldn't forget that
你一定不会原谅我的
You'd never forgive me
事实上 我自己还拍了电报给他
As a matter of fact, I sent him a telegram myself
欢迎比尔回家的生日派对 是一个历史的转折夜
(Margo) Bill's welcome-home birthday party, a night to go down in history
即使在派对还未开始之前 我都可感觉到会有事情发生
Even before the party started, I could smell disaster in the air
我早就知道,我很敏感 当我盛装之后就感觉到
I knew it I sensed it even as I finished dressing for that blasted party
-你都弄好了吗? -我后面拉链开了
-You all put together? -My back's open
他们有没有特别帮你? 大家都很卖面子
-Extra help get here? -There's some characters
尤其贝克 巴特勒, 还有那个叫威廉的经纪人
dressed as maids and butlers Did you call the William Morris Agency?
不好笑,我还不至没那行情 食物怎么样?
You're not funny Actors would cost less How about the food?
包办宴食的人回去拿开胃菜
The caterer had to go back for the hors d'oeuvres
那个法国佬可是教了你不少
That French ventriloquist taught you a lot
他真是无所不知
There was nothing he didn't know
酒保说,
There's a message from the bartender
嘉琳小姐订了琴酒 是不是搞错了?
"Does Miss Channing know that she ordered domestic gin by mistake?"
唯一订错的大概只有宾客
The only thing I ordered by mistake is the guests
跟他说,别在乎他们喝多少 只要不烧起来便行了
They don't care what they drink as long as it burns
-比尔迟到了? -什么迟到?
-Where's Bill? He's late -Late for what?
-我们要在派对上开舞呢!
Don't be dense The party
-他20分钟前就到了
I ain't dense He's been here for 20 minutes
那就奇怪了,怎么不上来呢?
Well, I certainly think it's odd he hasn't even come up to
你就别担心那些摄影师了
-(laughter) -The cameraman said,
即使他们也会看走眼
"Even DeMille couldn't see anything looking through the wrong end!" So
可别怪我挑剔 这种故事不适合成年人
Don't let me kill the point Or isn't it a story for grown-ups?
你听过的 当初我对你也是看走眼了
You've heard it I looked through the wrong end of the camera
这倒提醒我告诉你 当初我看起来是多么纯洁
Remind me to tell you about the time I looked into the heart of an artichoke
我倒想听听看 -这些事我不记得了
-I'd like to hear it -Some snowy night in front of the fire
现在我们来讨论一下问题,伊芙,你去查一下开胃菜
Meanwhile, would you check about the hors d'oeuvres, Eve?
或许他们忘了加热或什么的
The caterer forgot them The varnish wasn't dry or something
好的
Of course
看来我有个盛大的派对?
Looks like I'm going to have a fancy party
-我还以为你会迟到 -我是上宾吗?
-I thought you were going to be late -Well, I'm guest of honor
我真没想到你已经到了
I had no idea you were even here
伊芙在我上楼途中告诉我 你在更衣
I ran into Eve and she told me you were dressing
以前你从未留步呀!
That's never stopped you before
她一开口就跟我说 她想知道好莱坞的事 她似乎很感兴趣
She wanted to know about Hollywood She seemed so interested
她是个有很多兴趣的女孩 -在这年头是相当难得的美德
-She's a girl of so many interests -It's a pretty rare quality these days
这女孩还有相当多难得的美德 -她似乎是如此
-A girl of so many rare qualities -So she seems
难怪你常称赞她了
So you've pointed out so often
说她有多好
So many qualities so often
她的忠实,效率,卖力 而且又年轻 既年轻又美丽
Her loyalty, efficiency, devotion, warmth and affection, and so young
既年轻又美丽
So young and so fair
我无法相信你会编出这些话
I can't believe you're making this up
这根本就像低级闹剧一样
It sounds like something out of an old Clyde Fitch play
低级闹剧?你这么认为吗? 在我面前你可是一流的
Clyde Fitch, though you may not think so, was well before my time
我一向不否认 依美国人习性会对此吃惊的
I always deny that you were in Our American Cousin
林肯被刺的那天晚上
the night Lincoln was shot
我不认为这有什么好笑 这当然好笑
-I don't think that's funny -Of course it is
真是可笑到极点
This is all too laughable to be anything else
你知道我的感觉吗?我觉得你是不是到更年期了
You know what I feel about your age obsession
现在你这可笑的个性
And this getting into a jealous froth
你在为我跟个十岁孩子 聊十分钟吃什么醋?
because I spent ten minutes with a stage-struck kid
-20分钟 -30,40好了
-20! -30 minutes, 40 minutes What of it?
天真无邪,那正是少女特性
Stage-struck She's a young lady of qualities
我已厌烦她,还有她特性
And I'm fed up with both the young lady and her qualities
阅读我剧本,为我做笔记
Studying me as if I were a play or a blueprint
我如何走路,思考 表演,睡觉
How I walk, talk, think, act, sleep
你怎么可以大发脾气 就为那孩子想做得尽善尽美
How can you take offense at a kid trying to be like her ideal?
别再称她是孩子
Stop calling her a kid
对了,不过有个人要求我
As it happens, there are particular aspects of my life
保持一付唯我独尊的样子
to which I would like to maintain sole and exclusive rights and privileges
比方说什么呢? 比方说,你呀!
-For instance, what? -For instance, you
我现在任务该把你拥入怀里
This is my cue to take you in my arms and reassure you
但我不想这么做,我很生气
But I'm not going to I'm too mad
是罪恶感 是生气
-Guilty! -Mad!
达令,你有某些个性相当出名 不管是
There are certain characteristics for which you are famous,
在台上或台下
on stage and off
虽然有些个性是我喜欢的 但也有些我不喜欢
I love you for some and in spite of others I haven't let those become too important
那些个性成为我重要的部分,它们是你的利器之一 使你能立于不败之地
They're part of your equipment for getting along in what is called "our environment"
若你非得伶牙利齿,可以
You have to keep your teeth sharp, all right
但我绝不让你对我刻薄说话 或是对伊芙
But I will not have you sharpen them on me, or on Eve
那她寻我开心怎么说? 还有煽动 -她根本没有,你晓得的
-What about her teeth? Her fangs? -She hasn't cut them yet and you know it!
你开始幻想一个有梦想的孩子
So when you start judging an idealistic, dreamy-eyed kid
会在灯红酒绿的社会中胡来
by the bar-room, Benzedrine standards of this megalomaniac society,
我绝不同意
I won't have it!
伊芙从未对我说过话 只有建议,只有对你的崇拜
Eve Harrington has never by word, look, thought or suggestion
及对我们美满爱情的羡慕
indicated anything to me but adoration for you and happiness at our being in love
对我来说这不是吃醋
To intimate anything else
倒是一种狂妄与缺乏安全感 的举动,你该感到惭愧
spells a paranoiac insecurity that you should be ashamed of
停,她没有一样是真的
Cut Print it What happens in the next reel?
真的是我在无理取闹吗?
Do I get dragged off to the snake pits?
嘉琳小姐
(Eve) Miss Channing?
开胃菜到了!还有什么事要我做吗?
The hors d'oeuvres are here Is there anything else I can do?
谢谢你,伊芙 给我来杯马丁尼,纯的
Thank you, Eve I'd like a martini, very dry
我来倒!
I'll get it
你要喝什么? 一杯奶昔
-What'll you have? -A milk shake?
一杯马丁尼,纯的,麻烦你
A martini, very dry, please
-女士快点,宴会开始了 -比尔,你好
-The party's on the first floor -Hi, Bill
-你好,瑞奇太太 -亲爱的
-Hello, Mrs Richards -How are you, dear?
-你好伊芙 -晚上好瑞奇先生 -你好法宾先生
Good evening, Mr Richards, Mr Fabian
-大衣给我,好吗? -不用麻烦,我自己来
-May I have your coat? -I'll take it up
-让我来吧! -谢谢!
-Please -Thank you
-大家好 -你好
-Hi -Hi, Margo
-房子布置得很棒! -谢谢 -我喜欢那女孩
-The house looks lovely -I like that girl
气质很高雅
That quality of quiet graciousness
这只是她众多优点之一
Among so many quiet qualities
来吧!
Shall we?
玛歌你收容伊芙 是让我最快乐的事 -你高兴我就高兴了
-It's made me so happy your taking Eve in -I'm so happy you're happy
你们从未真正做过生意
You haven't been running a settlement house exactly
但都很有眼光
The kid has earned her way
你们得试试
You had a mixed-up inventory when she took over
默林零售商就买下不少了
Merchandise laying all over the shop
你要玛歌去做那些毛头小利
-You mixed Margo up with a five-and-ten -Make it Bergdorf Goodman
也许是个好主意 反正现在电影也玩不起来了
Everything on its proper shelf, eh, Max? All done up in little ribbons
现在就算我死了 也没人会在意的
I could die right now and nobody'd be confused
-麦斯,你呢? -我怎么了?
-How about you, Max? -How about me what?
要是你突然死了 你的财产要怎么办?
Suppose you dropped dead What about your inventory?
我不会突然死掉,现在不会
I ain't going to drop dead Not with the heat
这段谈话真是愉快
This is the most ghoulish conversation
-谢谢你 -没什么
-Thank you -Nothing
-麦斯!
Max! Mon vieux!
-谢飞!
Fife!
那孩子很快就会下来了 还是你想拿上去也可以
"The kid" will be down in a minute, unless you'd like to take her drink up to her
我知道该怎么做 -凯伦,给你
I can get a fresh one Karen, you're a Gibson girl
气氛好像很凝重
The general atmosphere is very Macbethish
发生什么事了? -他在说什么?
-What has or is about to happen? -What is he talking about?
-气氛凝重 -我们了解你,以前就发生过
-Macbeth -We've seen you like this before
事情是结束,还是才开始呢?
Is it over or is it just beginning?
绑好你们的安全带 这将会是个动荡的一夜
Fasten your seat belts It's going to be a bumpy night
-玛歌达令 -你好吗? -小姐!
-Margo, darling! -How are you?
-谢先生向你问好!
Mademoiselle, je vous remercie pour l'invitation
-也很高兴见到你
Enchantée to you too
我记得名单中好像没有你 你来做什么?
I remember, Addison, crossing you off my guest list What are you doing here?
你这令人难忘的小淘气 别再玩把戏了!
Dear Margo, you were an unforgettable Peter Pan You must play it again soon
-你记得凯丝维小姐吗? -不记得,你好!
-Remember Miss Casswell? -I do not How do you do?
我们没碰过面 -凯丝维小姐,是个演员
-We've never met Maybe that's why -She is an actress
库克班纳戏剧学院毕业生
A graduate of the Copacabana School of Dramatic Art
-伊芙
Ah Eve
-晚安,杜维特先生 -你们两位认识啊!
-Good evening, Mr DeWitt -I had no idea you knew each other
上次荣幸谋面后 一错身竟已过了这么久
This must be, at long last, our formal introduction
你不也是一错身 就认识我吗?
-Until now, we've only met in passing -That's how you met me In passing
伊芙,这位是杜先生的老友 他的母亲
Eve, this is an old friend of Mr DeWitt's mother
凯丝维小姐 她是哈林顿 -凯丝维小姐 -你好
-Miss Casswell, Miss Harrington -How do you do?
我看你很想跟伊芙小姐叙叙
I've been wanting you to meet Eve for the longest time
那我是恭敬不如从命
Your timidity must have kept you from mentioning it
-你该听听她对戏剧的高见 -那我们倒是有相同的喜好
-You know of her interest in the theatre? -We have that in common
那你们两个可以长谈了
Then you two must have a long talk
我想谈得太久 杜先生会觉得乏味的
I'm afraid Mr DeWitt would find me boring before too long
这你不必担心,或许你连 说话机会都没有
You won't bore him, honey You won't even get a chance to talk
亲爱的,你过来一下
Claudia, come here
你看那个人是制片人麦斯
You see that man? That's Max Fabian, the producer
过去好好自我推销一下
Now, go and do yourself some good
为何他们总像不快乐的兔子
Why do they always look like unhappy rabbits?
他们一向都是如此的 过去让他们开心一下
Cos that's what they are Now go and make him happier
你别担心?小迷人 她会很安全的
Now, don't worry about your little charge She'll be in safe hands
阿门!
Amen!
-弹“放荡者” -我刚弹过
-Liebestraum -I just played it
-再弹一遍 -已经第四遍了
-Play it again -But that was the fourth straight time
-那么就弹第五遍吧!
Then this will be five
你的那么多宾客不知道 你何时开舞呢?
Many of your guests are wondering when they may be permitted to view the body
而舞会在哪开呢? 舞会还没开
-Where has it been laid out? -It hasn't been laid out
我们酒没喝完
We haven't finished with the embalming
事实上你看到的玛歌.嘉琳
As a matter of fact, you're looking at it
只是她遗留的躯体
The remains of Margo Channing
呆坐着
sitting up
我的遗言是要坐着被埋葬
It is my last wish to be buried sitting up
你就没有更自然的姿势吗?
Wouldn't you feel more natural taking a bow?
你对感情不了解 自然或不自然的 是没有感情吧!
You know nothing about feelings, natural or unnatural
你的宾客都诧异着
Your guests were also wondering whether the music couldn't be
能否 弹奏较愉快的歌
a shade more on the, shall we say, happier side?
如果我的宾客不喜欢听
If my guests do not like it here,
我建议你和他们去疗养中心
I suggest they accompany you to the nursery
不然,我确信你们都会有 宾至如归的感觉
where I'm sure you will all feel more at home
玛歌,家里有小苏打吗?
Margo, you by any chance haven't got any bicarbonate of soda in the house?
可怜的麦斯,火烧心啊!
Poor Max Heartburn?
是因为凯丝维小姐吗?
It's that Miss Casswell
我不明白她为何不会令 艾德生火烧心?
I don't see why she hasn't given Addison heartburn
无心可痛呀!
No heart to burn
每个人都有颗心 除了某些人
Everybody has a heart, except some people
我当然有小苏打
Of course I've got bicarb
厨房架子上有一整盒
I've got a box in the pantry
我们会把你名字标上去 麦斯 法宾
We'll put your name on it "Max Fabian "
它会永远标在那里 只供你一人用
It will stay there always, just for you
让天下其他人去赚那些钱吧!
Let the rest of the world beat their brains out for a buck
还是朋友重要
It's friends that count
我有的是朋友 麦斯,我爱你 我是说真的
-And I have friends -I love you, Max I really mean it
我爱你
I love you
来餐具室
Come to the pantry
她爱我如父,她很清楚的
She loves me like a father Also, she's loaded
在这里,亲爱的麦斯
There you are, Maxie dear
只要一杯波本就可忘了凯小姐
One good burp and you'll be rid of that Miss Casswell
恐怕不成的
The situation I'm in ain't the kind you can belch your way out of
-我已保证过 -跟凯小姐吗?是什么呢?
-I made a promise -To Miss Casswell? What?
还不是为了电影“姐妹” 公开招考试演会
For an audition for this part we are replacing
她的名字叫什么，你的姐妹？
What's her name? Your sister?
-一匙 -不,二匙
-One? -No, two, please
她能演的,或许还不差
If she can act, she might not be bad
-看来她似乎可烧尽大伙儿
She looks like she might burn down a plantation
-只有我一个人遭殃而已
Right now, I feel like there is one burning in me
-试演会何时开始? -还有一,二个礼拜吧!
-When's the audition? -A couple of weeks
-由我来套台词
Tell you what Why don't I read with her?
-你愿意吗? -只要能帮你脱身
-Would you? -Anything to help you out, Max
-这才叫朋友,我很感激
Now that's cooperation I appreciate it
-别客气 -现在你可以帮我个大忙如果你愿意
Not at all And now you can do me a great favor
-尽管说
Just name it
在你公司给伊芙一份工作
Give Eve Harrington a job in your office
你的反应还真快
-(belches) -You get quick action, don't you?
我想都不会想 把那女孩从你身边带走
I wouldn't think of taking that girl away from you
你不是说我存货不够了
You said yourself my inventory was in shape,
我的商品也都发出去了
all my merchandise put away
留她在这也没事好做 只好把她送走
To keep her here with nothing to do, I'd be standing in her way
何况你需要她呀!麦斯 -她要做什么呢?
-And you need her, Max -What will she do?
她可帮上大忙的 阅读剧本
She'd be a great help She'd read scripts,
接见必要客人 推掉不必要的客人
interview people you have to see, get rid of those you don't have to
麦斯,那你会很清闲的
You'd be a man of leisure, Maxie
为自己多想想吧!
-Well -Think of your health
有更多时间在餐厅休息 呼吸新鲜的空气
More time to relax in the fresh air at a racetrack
-我不认为这意见很好 -答应我吧!
-I don't think it's such a good idea -Promise?
-我答应 -这才是好麦斯
-Promise -That's my Max
原来你们俩在这里
Oh, there you both are
麦斯,凯伦说要走了
Max, Karen's decided it's time to go
她现在人呢?-在你上面的房间
-Where is she now? -Up in your room
-失陪了!我去找凯小姐
If you'll excuse me, I'll go and tell Miss Casswell
-还有谁在呢? -很多
-Who's left out there? -Too many
对了,还有个客人 是来自好莱坞的影星
And, besides, you got a new guest, A movie star from Hollywood
夏克斯! 我把我的签名册送到各地
Shucks! And I sent my autograph book to the cleaners
-看得出你不太喜欢我这样
You disapprove of me when I'm like this, don't you?
-也不尽然 -有时我希望多了解你一点
Not exactly Sometimes, though, I wish I understood you better
-你要做时,通知我一声 -我会的
-When you do, let me in on it -I will
-那新来的怎样? -那部戏吗?我想还好吧!
-How's the new one coming? -The play? Oh, all right, I guess
蔻拉!又是个二十岁 女孩的故事
Cora Still a girl of 20?
二十岁并不重要
20-ish It's not important
难道你不觉得这是它 变得重要的时候吗?
Don't you think it's about time it became important?
-这话怎讲? -别装了
-How do you mean? -Don't be evasive
玛歌,你还不老嘛!
Margo, you haven't got any age
嘉琳小姐已上年纪了 说得跟记者一样好听
Miss Channing is ageless Spoken like a press agent
以我的身份来说 我晓得我在说什么
I know what I'm talking about They're my plays
语气就像作家一样
Spoken like an author
罗维,我不是二,三十岁
Lloyd, I'm not 20-ish I'm not 30-ish
四三个月前,我已经四十岁了
Three months ago I was 40 years old
四十岁!40!
40! Four-0
面对现实吧!
That slipped out
我已经下定决心去承认
I hadn't quite made up my mind to admit it
我突然觉得脱掉衣服 不晓得会是什么样子?
Now I suddenly feel as if I've taken all my clothes off
一周又一周,观众数以千计 你要多年轻就有多年轻
To thousands of people you're as young as you want
是他们要我那样年轻
As young as they want, you mean
我对数千观众认为我 六十或六百岁没兴趣
I'm not interested whether thousands of people think I'm six or 600
你只在乎一个人是吧!
Just one person, isn't that so?
你该知道那只是个故事 对吧!
You know what this is all about
跟你扮不扮演蔻拉没关系
It has little to do with whether you should play Cora
事实上你和比尔又吵架了
It has everything to do with you having a fight with Bill
比尔三十二岁 他看起来就像三十二岁
Bill's 32 He looks 32
他五年前是这模样 二十年后也会是这个模样
He looked it five years ago He'll look it 20 years from now
我讨厌男人
I hate men
罗维,别担心 你的戏我还是会演
Don't worry, Lloyd I'll play your play
如果你喜欢,我可戴上头套 甚至摇呼拉圈也行
I'll wear rompers and come in rolling a hoop, if you like
这时候会有谁来呢? 大家都该回家了呀!
Who'd show up at this hour? It's time people went home
把那大衣拿起来
Hold that coat up
谁的呢? 一个好莱坞来的电影影星
-Whose is it? -Some Hollywood movie star
她的飞机误点了 真叫人泄气,对吗?
-Her plane got in late -Discouraging, isn't it?
女人穿上这皮草就不冷了
Women with furs like that where it never even gets cold
好莱坞嘛!
Hollywood
伊芙告诉我,你过的如何? 快乐吗?
Tell me, Eve How are things going with you? Happy?
这是一个快乐的世界
There should be a new word for happiness
和嘉琳小姐在一起 我真说不上来
Being here with Miss Channing has been a, I just can't say
她太好了,帮我做很多事
She's been so wonderful, done so much for me
罗维说,玛歌决定以
Lloyd says Margo compensates for underplaying on stage
真实年龄来演出
by overplaying reality
下次舞会,貂皮大衣看起来 像是件旧大衣而已
Next to that sable, my new mink seems like an old bed jacket
伊芙,你尽力了 你和玛歌配合的很好 -晚安!
You've done your share, Eve You've worked wonders with Margo Good night
-瑞奇太太 -叫凯伦就好
-Mrs Richards? -Karen
-凯伦
Karen
我正打算求你帮忙
Isn’t it awful? I'm about to ask you for another favor,
其实你已经帮了我
after all you've done already
其实也没人帮你忙
Nobody's done so much
你不该再这么想 认为自己多么需要帮忙
Stop thinking of yourself as one of the hundred neediest cases
什么事呢? 嘉琳小姐事业正如日中天
-What is it? -Miss Channing's affairs are in good shape,
我现在也不怎么忙了
so there isn't enough to keep me as busy as I should be
我并不想抢走她什么东西
Not that I'd consider anything that would take me away from her
但是前几天 我听法宾先生告诉嘉琳小姐
But the other day when Mr Fabian told Miss Channing
法宾的新戏有个角色 他们打算要用别人代替
that her understudy was going to have a baby and they'd have to replace her
你想代替玛歌的角色 我是不敢这么想
-You wanna be Margo's new understudy? -I don't let myself think about it even
但那角色我相当的熟 还有各种台步
But I do know the part so well, and every bit of the staging,
他们不必再找别的女孩
there'd be no need to break in a new girl
只是那天晚上观众只要看
Suppose I had to go on one night
嘉琳小姐的戏
to an audience that came to see Margo Channing
-那是不可能的了 -这点我就不太担心了
-Oh, no, I couldn't possibly! -I wouldn't worry too much about that
玛歌的表演是不会失误的 只要她能走,能爬,能滚 她就能演出
Margo just doesn't miss performances If she can walk, crawl or roll, she plays
戏还会继续演下去 不,玛歌还会继续演下去
-The show must go on -No, dear Margo must go on
事实上我不明白 你为何不可上她的新戏?
I don't see any reason why you shouldn't be her understudy
-你认为嘉琳小姐会同意吗? -我认为她会很高兴
-You think Miss Channing would approve? -I think she'd cheer
但瑞奇和辛普森先生呢? 他们会听命行事
-But Mr Richards and Mr Sampson? -They'll do as they're told
-你会替我向法宾先生说吗?
Then would you speak to Mr Fabian about it?
-当然 -你不会忘记
-Of course -You won't forget?
-我不会忘记的
I won't forget
看来我得永远感谢你这朋友
I seem to be forever thanking you for something, don't I?
这些看来就像一堆死畜牲
-The bed looks like a dead animal act -(Karen chuckles)
哪一件是貂皮呢? -她不是才刚到吗?
-Which one is sable? -But she just got here
-不到半分钟就找到伴走了
Well, she's on her way with half the men in the joint
我才不需要皮草呢! 你不想要一件貂皮大衣吗?
-It's only a fur coat -What do you expect? Live sable?
钻石,打牌,黄金,睡觉 任你挑啊!
Diamond collar, gold sleeves You know, picture people
其实舞台上的老牌演员 或电影圈人士
(Addison) Elder statesmen of the theatre or cinema
呈现给大众的 是他们所扮的角色
assure the public that actors and actresses are just plain folks,
却忽略了他们吸引大众 与现实人生是完全不同的
ignoring the fact that their greatest attraction to the public
女人可以为其牺牲
is their complete lack of resemblance to normal human beings
或许更胜一层呢?
Now there's something a girl could make sacrifices for
-目标是什么? -为貂皮
-And probably has -Sable
-你是说貂皮?还是狐皮? -其中一个
-Sable? Did she say sable or Gable? -Either one
我们彼此都有这共通点
We all have abnormality in common
圈内人的个性都是大同小异
We're a breed apart from the rest of humanity, we theatre folk
我们是人性的原始写照
We are the original displaced personalities
我们明晚不必看他专栏了 各位刚刚已经听到了
You won't have to read his column tomorrow, Eve You just heard it
我不同意你的看法,艾德生 或许你没有这种习性
-I don't agree, Addison -That's your particular abnormality
我承认圈内有些害群之马
I admit there's a screwball element in the theatre
外表风风光光 台上受万人注目
It sticks out, it's got spotlights on it and a brass band
但这是基本的,可以忍受的 没有他们电影根本不能生存
But it isn't basic It isn't standard If it were, the theatre couldn't survive
服务生
Oh, waiter
亲爱的,那不是服务生 是佣人
That isn't a waiter, my dear That's a butler
我不想叫他佣人行吗?
Well, I can't yell out "butler", can I?
或许有人名叫佣人
Maybe somebody's name is Butler
你很有观点,虽然笨了点 但终究是个论点
You have a point An idiotic one, but a point
我不想惹麻烦,只想喝杯酒
I don't wanna make trouble All I want is a drink
让我来吧!我替你倒一杯 谢谢你,法宾先生
-Leave it to me I'll get you one -Thank you, Mr Fabian
做得好! 看得出你事业会像旭日东升
Well done I can see your career rising in the east like the sun
你刚才说 -我说影剧圈十之八九 都是苦差事
You were saying? -The theatre is nine-tenths hard work
需要辛劳工作,并配合 血汗,机运和专业素养
Work done the hard way, by sweat, application and craftsmanship
这点我同意 影剧圈要成为杰出男女演员
To be a good actor or actress, or anything in the theatre,
是世上最困难的事
means wanting to be that more than anything else
是的,的确是那样
Yes Yes, it does
没有哪个行业需要如此 专心,渴望,野心及牺牲
It means a concentration of desire or ambition and sacrifice
所以我认为能接受它的人
such as no other profession demands
可说不同凡响
And the man or woman who accepts those terms can't be ordinary,
一般人是无法忍受的
can't be just someone
付出这么多,收获却这么少
To give so much for almost always so little
这么少?
"So little?"
这么少? 你是说收获这么少?
"So little," did you say?
没有任何东西比得上喝采
Why, if there's nothing else, there's applause
我在后台听到观众的喝采声
I've listened backstage to people applaud
就像
It's like
爱的浪潮 从席上涌来,围绕着你
Like waves of love coming over the footlights and wrapping you up
想想看每个表演之夜 数以百计不同的人热爱着你
Imagine, to know every night that different hundreds of people love you
他们微笑,发出异彩眼光 你取悦了他们
They smile, their eyes shine, you've pleased them
他们需要你,你属于他们
They want you You belong
所以没什么好计较
Just that alone is worth anything
不必起来 不必装得我像皇太后似的
Don't get up And please stop acting as if I were the Queen Mother
抱歉 在蜜蜂世界中,玛歌
-I'm sorry, I didn't -Outside of a beehive, Margo,
你很难不被认为是只女王蜂
your behavior is hardly queenly or motherly
兄弟,你也在我的蜂巢中 你不晓得吗?
You're in a beehive, pal
我们都是忙碌的小蜜蜂 日以继夜地在造蜜
We're all busy little bees, full of stings, making honey day and night
-不是吗,宝贝? -玛歌!你真是的
-Aren't we, honey? -Margo, really
凯伦,别装成女州长模样
Please don't play governess, Karen
我受够你那高尚的品味
I haven't your unyielding good taste
我希望我也能去打网球 可是爸爸却不准
I wish I could have gone to Radcliffe, too, but Father wouldn't hear of it
我想他是个老顽固 现在该说是老古板
He needed help behind a notions counter
或是我应该说老头
I'm being rude now, aren't I? Or should I say, ain't I?
你实在是可怜 我看你是太紧张了
You're maudlin and full of self-pity You're magnificent
今晚就这样结束吧!
How about calling it a night?
你摆出一副编剧的样子
And you pose as a playwright
此场此景,你能想到的 却是大家都去睡吧!
A situation pregnant with possibilities, and all you can think of is "go to sleep "
-这是个好构想啊! -这样演不下去了
-It's a good thought -It won't play
以一个圈外人来说 我有个绝妙点子,对不起
As a nonprofessional, I think it's an excellent idea Excuse me
虽然不太浪漫,但很实际
Undramatic, perhaps, but practical
-快乐的家庭主妇 -打住!
-Happy little housewife -Cut it out
这是我家,不是剧院 在我家是客人,不是个导演
This is my house, not a theatre In my house you're a guest, not a director
别摆出一副大明星的架子 别把你客人都当成配角
Then stop being a star and treating your guests as your supporting cast
别火上加油了 该是死的时候了
-Let's not get into a big hassle -It's time we did
让玛歌了解 台上能吸引人,下了台就未必
Margo has to realize what's attractive on stage need not be attractive off
好了!
All right!
我要去睡了
I'm going to bed
由你当主人,这是你派对 生日快乐,欢迎回家
You be host It's your party Happy birthday Welcome home
-我们的问题待会再解决
And we who are about to die salute you
-需要帮忙吗?
Need any help?
要抱我上床吗? 脱掉我衣服,扶着我头
To put me to bed? Take my clothes off, hold my head?
钻进被窝,关灯和我甜言蜜语
Tuck me in, turn out the lights and tiptoe out?
你想要吗?伊芙
Eve would, wouldn't you, Eve?
-如果你愿意 -我才不愿意
-If you'd like -I wouldn't like
-我忘了还拿着 -我记得
-Oh, I forgot I had it -I didn't
太可惜,我们错过第三幕
Too bad We're gonna miss the third act
我也将错过演出了
They're gonna play it offstage
-麦斯,要一起来吗? -等一下
-Coming, Max? -In a minute
伊芙,你千万别跟我一样 介意玛歌的态度
Eve, you mustn't mind Margo too much, even if I do
不,一定有某种理由 是我做错了什么
There must be some reason, something I've done without knowing
原因在玛歌自己,别去想了 只有爱因斯坦才知道
The reason is Margo and don't try to figure it out Einstein couldn't
我觉得我该为她 向大家解释一下
But if I thought I'd offended her, of all people
伊芙,我也喜欢玛歌
Eve I'm fond of Margo, too
但我了解玛歌 经常
But I know Margo And every now and then,
我最想做的一件事 就是一脚踢在她屁股上
there is nothing I wanna do so much as kick her right square in the pants
她总是找人出气
Well, if she has to pick on someone,
我想大概就是我吧!
I'd just as soon it was me
-麦斯要送我们回去 -晚安!
-Max is gonna drop us -Good night
-晚安
-Good night -Good night
瑞奇太太 你不会忘记吧! 我们不久前谈好的事
Mrs Richards? You won't forget, will you? What we talked about before?
伊芙,我不会忘记的
No, Eve I won't forget
为何自己一个人呢?艾德生
Why so remote, Addison?
我想你这制片也该给她打气
You should be at the side of your protégée, lending her moral support
我现在不需要给她打气
Miss Casswell is where I can lend no support, moral or otherwise
小姐,在休息室吧?
In the ladies' shall we say "lounge"?
她肚子痛
Being violently ill to her tummy
这是试演前的好兆头 在开演前她会没事的
It's good luck before an audition
凯小姐的好运来得太迟了 试演会结束了
Miss Casswell got lucky too late The audition is over
怎么可能呢? 我是来跟凯小姐对台词的 我答应过麦斯
It can't be I came here to read with Miss Casswell I promised Max
试演通告是两点半 现在都四点了
The audition was at 2 30 It's now nearly four
真的?我得开始学戴手表了 你知道我从不戴表的吗?
Is it really? I must start wearing a watch I never have, you know
那么凯小姐的台词谁来对呢?
Who read with Miss Casswell?
-比尔? -不是 -罗维? -不是
-Bill? Lloyd? -No
-更不可能是麦斯,会是谁呢? -当然是由替代的人来
-Well, it can't have been Max Who? -Naturally, your understudy
我认为由那位怀孕的代角 来饰演是很不自然的
It's unnatural to allow a girl in an advanced state of pregnancy
我听说你有一位新的代角 她没怀孕,她是伊芙.哈林顿
I refer to your new and unpregnant understudy, Miss Eve Harrington
-伊芙?我的替代角色?
Eve? My understudy?
-难道你不晓得? 我当然知道
-Didn't you know? -Of course I knew
只不过突然忘了
It just slipped your mind?
那凯丝维小姐呢?
How was Miss Casswell?
坦白说,我不记得了
Frankly, I don't remember
-只是突然忘了? -全忘了
-Just slipped your mind? -Completely
我确信目前也无人能告诉你 凯小姐的演技如何?
Nor can anyone else present tell you how Miss Casswell read,
或是凯小姐会不会演出?
or whether Miss Casswell read or rode a pogo stick
她真的这么差吗?
Was she that bad?
玛歌,就如你所知 我这一生都活在戏剧中
Margo, I have lived in the theatre as a Trappist monk lives in his faith
如同修道之人一样 我没有别的世界及生活
I have no other world, no other life
我曾历经一些伟大的改革时期
Once in a great while, I experience that moment of revelation
那些都使我的祈祷成为真实 你是其中一位
for which all true believers wait and pray You were one
金妮是另一位 还有鲍儿 维丝礼,海丝 还有其它三,四位大明星
Jeanne Eagels another, Paula Wessely, Hayes There are others, three or four
伊芙.哈林顿也将会在其中
Eve Harrington will be among them
我相信,她的确很不错
I take it she read well
那不是念对白,是场表演
It wasn't a reading, it was a performance
出色而绝妙,并经音乐润饰
Brilliant, vivid, something made of music and fire
多好啊!
How nice
假以时日她会变成第二个你
In time, she'll be what you are
需要音乐润饰
A mass of music and fire
我可演出毫无缺点
That's me An old kazoo with some sparklers
告诉我,比尔赞成吗?
Tell me, was Bill swept away, too?
还是你们二人得突破改革
Or were you too full of revelation to notice?
比尔,并没有说什么
Bill didn't say
但罗维却专心听她的对话
But Lloyd listened to his play
就像听别人的作品一样
as if it had been written by someone else, he said
那么新鲜,振奋人心
It sounded so fresh, so new, so full of meaning
那对罗维来说太好了 对伊芙也太好了 对大家都好呀!
How nice for Lloyd How nice for Eve How nice for everybody
伊芙却非常谦虚 她坚持自己不算什么
Eve was incredibly modest She insisted that no credit was due her
罗维认为她的表演完全 合乎他笔下描写的角色
That Lloyd felt as he did because she read his lines exactly as he'd written them
你是说我演得不好?
The implication being that I did not read them as written?
对话时我没提到你名字 或影射你的表演
Neither your name nor your performance entered the conversation
感觉好多了吗?亲爱的
Ah! Feeling better, my dear?
我好像刚上过英国电台 现在又怎么了?
Like I just swam the English Channel Now what?
你下个目标是打进电视圈
Your next move, it seems to me, should be towards television
告诉我电视也有试演会吗?
Tell me this Do they have auditions for television?
电视呀!除了试演还是试演
That's all television is, my dear Nothing but auditions
玛歌达令!
Oh, Margo, darling
抱歉!来迟了,午餐拖太久 找不到计程车
Terribly sorry I was late Lunch was long and I couldn't find a cab
凯小姐呢?我们可开始了吗? -你好!伊芙 -嘉琳小姐,你好
-Where's Miss Casswell? Oh, hello, Eve -Hello, Miss Channing
你怎么找到法宾先生办公室?
How are you making out in Mr Fabian's office?
麦斯,你别太折磨这孩子
Now, Max, I don't want you working this child too hard
你答应过我
just because you promised
就如同我也信守我的承诺
As you see, I kept my promise, too
一切都结束了
It's all over
-什么结束了? -试演会
-What's all over? -The audition
伊芙表演给凯小姐看了 伊芙?太妙了!
-Eve read with Miss Casswell -Eve? How enchanting
你们两个怎么想到这点子 让伊芙来对凯丝维的台词
How did you get the idea of letting Eve read with Miss Casswell?
她是你的临时替角呀! 伊芙?我的临时替角? 我怎么不知道
-Well, she's your understudy -Eve? My understudy? I had no idea
我以为你知道 她一礼拜前就开始做了
I thought you knew She started a week ago
这实在难以想象 我从没见过她到后台
I've never seen her backstage,
当然这工作是很多人想要的
but with so many people loitering about Well, well
伊芙根本不是替麦斯工作
So Eve is not working for Max, after all
麦斯,你这大滑头
Max, you sly puss
嘉琳小姐 我心中有说不出的高兴 -但你这么晚才到
Miss Channing, I can't tell you how glad I am that you arrived so late
-真的?为什么呢?
Really, Eve? Why?
如果你一开始就在这里 我绝不敢对台词的
Otherwise, I never would have dared to read
有何不可呢? 如果你是半夜来
-Why not? -If you'd come in the middle,
无疑地 我绝不敢这么做的
I couldn't have gone on
太可惜了! 所有灯火及音乐都被关掉了
What a pity All that fire and music being turned off
-什么灯火和音乐? -你绝不会明白的
-What fire and music? -You wouldn't understand
凯丝维小姐表现如何呢?
How was Miss Casswell?
回库克班纳戏剧学校去了
Back to the Copacabana
但是伊芙,玛歌 我来跟你谈谈伊芙
But Eve, Margo Let me tell you about Eve
嘉琳小姐,我吓死了 相信我
I was dreadful, Miss Channing
我无权担任任何人的替角 尤其是你的
I have no right to be anyone's understudy, much less yours
我看你是低估自己了 你一向是如此的!
I'm sure you underestimate yourself You always do
你们不是要跟我讲伊芙吗?
You were about to tell me about Eve
-你真该为她骄傲 -这我确定
-You'd have been proud of her -I'm sure
-她是个天才 -你们两个也是
-She was a revelation -Oh, to you too?
-这话是什么意思? -我是说其它的事
-What do you mean by that? -It must have been a revelation
那么这铁定是24岁的角色 由24岁的演员来演
to have a 24-year-old character played by a 24-year-old actress
-你把话题扯远了 -这绝对正中话题
-That's beside the point -It is the point
这个演出一定很新鲜
It must have seemed so new and fresh to you,
你一定很兴奋吧! 那些台词就如同出自你手笔
so exciting, to have your lines read just as you wrote them
艾德生! 那表演是多么有意义 火花以及音乐旋律
-Addison -So full of meaning, fire and music
你的口气就像是艾德生夫人
You've talked to that venomous fishwife DeWitt
这次看来我信任的人 都已经刊在世界年鉴上了
In this case, as trustworthy as the world almanac
你知道你进来,试演会已结束 伊芙只是你的代角
You knew when you came in that Eve was your understudy
代替你游戏,用嘴对词而已
Playing that childish game of cat and mouse
不是嘴,是些鼠辈行径
Not mouse Never mouse If anything, rat
以你的天份,如此误解
Your genius for making a bar-room brawl
一个完全无辜的女孩
out of a perfectly innocent misunderstanding
完全无辜? 我看我去上吊好了
Perfectly innocent? Men have been hanged for less
我对她说了谎吗? 她背后攻击我
I'm lied to, attacked behind my back,
归罪于你的烂对话 或是你的上帝
accused of reading your play as if it were the holy gospel
我从未这么说过
I never said it was
你何时听到有人读你的剧本? 你理想人选是谁?
You listen as if someone else had written your play Whom do you have in mind?
亚瑟 米勒?谢武德 波玛和费雪吗?
Arthur Miller? Sherwood? Beaumont and Fletcher?
-我能说句话吗? -不行!
-May I say a word? -No!
你认为亚瑟 米勒和谢武德 会像我这样忍受你胡来?
You think Miller or Sherwood would stand for the nonsense I take from you?
你最好跟波玛和费雪一起 他们已死了三百年了
Stick to Beaumont and Fletcher They've been dead for 300 years!
所有剧作家早该在 三百年前就死了
All playwrights should be dead for 300 years!
那根本不能解决问题 因为女演员是不朽的
That would solve none of their problems because actresses never die!
明星是不朽且不变的
The stars never die and never change
你可随时变更明星
You may change this star any time you want
成为夸张而刺激的新星 充满火爆音乐,
for a new and fresh and exciting one, fully equipped with fire and music
随心所欲 由夜间秀开头好了
Any time you want, starting with tonight's performance
这些让律师来解决吧!
This is for lawyers to talk about
这关系到所有的戏剧 你不能胡来
This concerns a contract that you cannot rewrite or ad-lib
法宾先生,你威胁对我 采取法律行动吗?
Are you threatening me with legal action, Mr Fabian?
-你要破坏合约吗? -回答我的问题
-Are you breaking the contract? -Answer my question
我一点办法也没有 就像死人一样 -我没听到
-Who am I to threaten? I'm a dying man -I don't hear you
-我说我是个垂死的人 -除非这世界上
-I said I'm a dying man! -Not until the last drugstore
没卖药的药房
has sold its last pill
我真不明白是如何演变的
I shall never understand the process by which a body with a voice
而使得身躯和声音 突然幻想它自己是心智
suddenly fancies itself as a mind
是何时开始由女演员决定
Just when does an actress decide
她所说的话及所表达的思想
they're her words she's saying and her thoughts she's expressing?
通常从她重写并重新思考开始
Usually at the point when she has to rewrite and rethink them
为了避免观众远离戏院
to keep the audience from leaving the theatre
该让钢琴手了解协奏曲 但并非他所写的
It's about time the piano realized it has not written the concerto!
你!我认为是帕特瑞斯基 他使我在钢琴上弹出协奏曲
And you, I take it, are the Paderewski who plays his concerto on me, the piano?
-音乐里的点火公主呢?
Where is Princess Fire and Music?
-谁? -那个孩子
-Who? -The kid Junior
新来的走了 -我一定把她吓走了
-Gone -I must have frightened her away
我一点也不意外 有时你令我吃惊
I wouldn't be surprised Sometimes you frighten me
可怜的小东西 抓紧裤子,弃甲而逃
Poor little flower Dropped her petals and folded her tent
-别胡闹啦! -我就是要闹
-Don't mix your metaphors -I'll mix what I like!
什么都不是,只有躯体和声音 没有思想
I'm nothing but a body with a voice No mind
多美的躯体!多美的声音
What a body What a voice
那个耶修新闻记者 没有躯体声音,充满思想
That ex ship-news reporter No body, no voice, all mind
雨停了,战争结束了! 冷静吧!
The gong rang, the fight's over, calm down
-我才不要冷静
I will not calm down
-那就不要冷静
Don't calm down
-你真是宽宏大量 -我尽了全力
-You're being terribly tolerant, aren't you? -I'm trying terribly hard
-不必如此 -我不要别人宽容我 我也不要别人来挑剔我
Well, you needn't be I will not be tolerated and I will not be plotted against
又来了 真是无聊,你当我是什么?
-Here we go -Such nonsense What do you take me for?
乡下的土女人?
Little Nell from the country?
没通知我一声 就偷偷的代了一星期
Been my understudy for a week without me knowing it
一定是偷偷摸摸的 别冲动
-Carefully hidden, no doubt -Don't get carried away
这里的试演会 大家都知道我要来
Arrives here for an audition when everyone knows I will be here,
不管到哪里都由我演出 你已跟罗维说好了,不是吗?
-and gives a performance out of nowhere -You've been all through that with Lloyd
剧作家是不过问演出 但他却如此,这次可不行
The playwright doesn't make the performance It doesn't just happen
火爆的音乐有何不可?
Full of fire and music and whatnot
一定是谨慎地排演过
Carefully rehearsed, I have no doubt
竟是些比尔和辛普森要的人
Full of those Bill Sampson touches
-你这种胡闹妄想症真烦人 -妄想症?
-I am tired of these paranoiac outbursts -Paranoiac?
今天下午2点半我才知道 伊芙.哈林顿是你的候补演员
I didn't know Eve was your understudy until this afternoon
告诉福特大夫要我休长假吧!
Tell that to Dr Freud along with the rest of it
不!我要告诉你 我最后一次告诉你
No, I'll tell it to you for the last time
你必须停止以这种妄想症 来伤害我们彼此
Cos you've got to stop hurting the two of us by these paranoiac tantrums
又是我吗? 我连它是什么都不知道
That word I don't even know what it means
我总算找到适当时机了
It's time you found out
我爱你 我爱你
-I love you I love you -Hah!
你美丽且有才华 一个没有声音的驱体
-You're beautiful and intelligent -A body with a voice
一个美丽又有才华的女人 也是伟大的女演员
A beautiful and an intelligent woman, and a great actress
伟大女演员事业前途无量 你绝对有权得到幸福
A great actress at the peak of her career You have every reason for happiness
-幸福除外 -绝对有权的
-Except happiness -Every reason
但却做出这些奇怪失控 孩子气的行为
But due to some uncontrollable drive, you permit the slightest action of a kid
什么孩子? 孩子气,甚至使你变得 经常歇斯底里尖叫
-A kid! -a kid to turn you into a screaming harpy
以后别再这样了
Now, once and for all, stop it
显然你不是女人
It's obvious you're not a woman
这点我还知道 -但我是
-I've been aware of that for some time -Well, I am
-又怎么说
I'll say
不要这么低俗了
Don't be condescending
快起来!我请你喝一杯
Come on, get up I'll buy you a drink
我承认我是比以前如意
I may have seen better days,
但还没有喝鸡尾酒的身价
but I'm still not to be had for the price of a cocktail
像个咸花生
Like a salted peanut
玛歌,我们谈和吧! 条件很高,要无条件投降
-Margo, let's make peace -The terms are too high
只是开心一下 停止这些为伊芙的无聊争执
Just being happy? Just stopping all this nonsense about Eve?
连我也不行吗? 一点也不无聊
-And Eve and me? -It's not nonsense
若我告诉你刚才是我做的 你会听吗?
But if I tell you it is, as I just did, were you listening to me?
-这还不够吗? -但愿是
-Isn’t that enough? -I wish it were
那么该怎样才够?
Then what would be enough?
我们结婚好吗?
If we got married?
我不要你为了 证明某件事而娶我
I wouldn't want you to marry me just to prove something
你有这么多理由拒绝我
You've had so many reasons for not wanting to marry me
玛歌告诉我,到底什么问题?
Margo, tell me what's behind all this
我我不知道,比尔
I don't know, Bill
只是一种感觉,我不知道
It's just a feeling I don't know
我想你很清楚
I think you do know
但你不愿或不能告诉我
But you won't or can't tell me
我以前说过这是最后尝试 这是真的
I said before it was gonna be my last try, and I meant it
我完全没办法,但愿我能做到
I can't think of anything else to do I wish I could
我们总在落幕时尖叫丢东西
We usually wind up screaming as the curtain comes down
等幕再升起时再和好
Then it comes up again and everything's fine
但这次不会了
But not this time
你知道这是世间的一部戏
No playwright in the world could make me believe
能让我相信在两个成人间 会发生这种事
this would happen between two adult people
再见!玛歌
Goodbye, Margo
比尔!
Bill?
你要去哪里?
Where are you going?
去找伊芙吗?
To find Eve?
这句话使一切变得更可信了
That suddenly makes the whole thing believable
罗维
去找伊芙吗?
Lloyd
罗维,怎么了? -火死了!满肚子火
-Lloyd, what's happened? -Up to here, that's where I've got it
-那明星胆大妄为,歇斯底里的
Of all the star-ridden, presumptuous, hysterical
-又是玛歌? 一而再再而三迟到
-Margo again -And again and again
使试演会晚两小时才开始 玛歌是会这样的
-Two hours late for the audition -That's on time for Margo
依惯例迟到又孩子气 不知道自己是候补演员
And then a childish routine about not knowing Eve was her understudy
-她不知道呀 -她当然知道
-It's possible she didn't -She knew
艾德生告诉她 伊芙如何优异诠释那个角色
Addison told her how superbly Eve had read the part
凯伦!我跟你说伊芙 她具有所有条件
Karen, let me tell you about Eve She's got everything A born actress
是天生演员敏锐,善解人意 年轻,活跃,精力充沛
Sensitive, understanding, young, exciting
-一点缺点都没有吗?
You'll run out of adjectives, dear
-具备一切编剧想写的优点
Everything a playwright first thinks of wanting to write about,
直到这部剧成为嘉琳独角戏
until his play becomes a vehicle for Miss Channing
玛歌演得不好吗?
Margo hasn't done badly by it
玛歌很棒,她知道 麻烦在这里
Margo's great She knows it, that's the trouble
她演得可好了 还要指派谁来配戏
She can play Peck's Bad Boy all she wants and who's to stop her?
谁能让她随心所欲呢?
Who's to give her that boot in the rear she needs and deserves?
这会是个很冷的周末
It's gonna be a cozy weekend
你说什么呀! 明晚我们开车去乡下
-What is? -We're driving to the country tomorrow
就我们四个人 比尔,玛歌,你跟我
Just the four of us Bill, Margo, you and I
我们以前也度过这种周末 但也不怎么样
Well, we've spent weekends before with nobody talking
要确定锁上那会致伤的器具 和会摔烂的东西
Just be sure to lock up all blunt instruments and throwable objects
他们说牛顿发现地心引力
(Karen) Newton, they say,
因看到苹果打在人的头上
thought of gravity by getting hit on the head by an apple
发明蒸气机的人
And the man who invented the steam-engine,
是看到茶壶
he was watching a teakettle
但不是我 我坐在沙发想到好点子
But not me My big idea came to me just sitting on a couch
那个情绪不稳的玛歌 根本不知道有事了
That boot in the rear to Margo Heaven knows, she had one coming
因我,罗维,伊芙,比尔 麦斯等人之故
From me, from Lloyd, from Eve, Bill, Max and so on
我们常为这件事感到伤神
We'd all felt those size fives of hers often enough
但怎么办?答案在我心中翻滚
But how? The answer was buzzing around me like a fly
灵机一现
I had it
但我又放弃了 尖声呼叫名字是一回事
But I let it go Screaming and calling names is one thing,
但这意谓着
but this could mean
有何不可呢? 为什么? 我对我自己说,玛歌
Why not? "Why," I said to myself, "not?"
那好像很合理
It would all seem perfectly legitimate
而全世界只有两个人会知道
And only two people in the world would know
而且对每个人都有好处
Also, the boot would land where it would do the most good for all concerned
毕竟那只是无伤大雅的玩笑
After all, it was no more than a harmless joke
玛歌自己将是最开心的
which Margo herself would be the first to enjoy
根本没有理由不告诉她 所以我就
And no reason why she shouldn't be told about it, in time
麻烦你接伊芙.哈林顿听电话
Hello Will you please call Miss Eve Harrington to the phone?
没关系,我等
Not at all I'll wait
那对屋外的人是个寒冷周未
(Karen) It was a cold weekend, outside and in
没见到比尔人影
Bill didn't come at all
玛歌不知道她的处境 她根本不在乎,话说个不停
Margo didn't know where he was and didn't care, she kept saying
过了礼拜天
Somehow we staggered through Sunday,
周一下午 我们送玛歌到车站时
and by the time we drove Margo to the station late Monday afternoon,
她和罗维考虑要彼此以礼相待
she and Lloyd had thawed out to the extent of being civil to each other
现在几点了?
What time is it?
一分钟前是5点42分
When you asked a minute ago, it was 5 42
现在是5点43分 -一分钟后你再问就是
It is now 5 43 When you ask again a minute from now
-我只是不要玛歌误了火车 -几点会到戏院?
I just don't want Margo to miss her train As it is, she'll barely make the theatre
-5点55分,我们到车站时间还很足够
5 55 We'll be at the station in plenty of time
那小地方距纽约只要两小时
That little place "just two hours from New York "
我这呆头脑很难了解
It's on my list of things I'll never understand,
住在那落伍的印第安社区
like collecting shrunken Indian heads
一般人你该了解的 想要一点点安静及和平
You should know what it means to want a little peace and quiet
安静和平是属于图书馆的
Peace and quiet is for libraries
-罗维,拜托!
Lloyd Please
-只是滑了一下 这些路像玻璃
Just a little skid, that's all This road's like glass
-凯伦和我不希望出意外 -我并不想造成意外啊!
-Karen and I just don't want an accident -I don't intend to have an accident
那对你会比较危险 我们都穿了长内衣
It isn't important whether you do We are wearing long underwear
这是怎么回事?
Now what's this?
不可能,不可能没汽油的
But it can't be We can't be out of gas
我昨天亲自加的油 -你今早开到伯斯特家 不是满的吗?
I filled it myself yesterday Wasn't it full when you drove to Brewster this morning?
我没看 你知道我从不注意那些的
I didn't look You know I don't pay attention to those things
-简直难以置信
Just incredible
-我们还有多少时间? -大约十分钟
-How much time have we got? -Roughly ten minutes
-车站有多远? 大约3,4哩路
-How far is the station? -About three or four miles
附近有房子或农庄吗? 我们可借点汽油 这种荒僻的路上
-Any houses where we can borrow gas? -There's not much along this back road
不会有多大机会可搭到便车
Not many cars either Not much chance of a lift
没关系,你们坐在这里等 我向前走,说不定会有机会
No sense in sitting here I'm gonna walk up about half a mile, just in case
-你要听吗? -没关系
-You want it on? -It doesn't matter
我的格调不高
I detest cheap sentiment
凯伦!
-Karen? -Mm-hm?
不要,谢谢
No, thank you
这周末我心情很坏 最近我们都有点紧张
-I haven't been very pleasant this weekend -We've all been a little tense lately
想想我几星期来都很快乐
Come to think of it, I haven't been very pleasant for weeks
对那件事我实在抱歉
For that, I'm truly sorry
你们和我最知心 我不要你和罗维生我的气
More than any two people I know, I don't want you and Lloyd to be angry with me
我们不是真的生气 只是不高兴你的作法
We're never deeply angry We just get mad the way you do
我们知道你做得很好
We know you too well
有那么多人认识我
So many people know me
我真希望有人说说我的事
I wish I did I wish someone would tell me about me
-你是玛歌,就是玛歌
You're Margo Just Margo
-那是什么意思? 生命里的灿烂时刻
And what is that? Besides something spelled out in light bulbs, I mean
那也只是暂时的 那大部份只是我的青春
Besides a temperament, which consists mostly of swooping about on a broomstick
和我的尖叫声
and screaming at the top of my voice
我的行为很幼稚
Infants behave the way I do, you know
我不断的犯错 只有在酒醉时才清醒
They carry on and misbehave They'd get drunk if they knew how,
但还是不能如我所愿
when they can't have what they want
当感到不被需要或不安全感
When they feel unwanted or insecure or
或不被爱时
unloved
-比尔呢? -比尔怎么了?
-What about Bill? -What about Bill?
他爱你
He's in love with you
我爱比尔超过世上所有东西 我要比尔…
More than anything in this world, I love Bill And I want Bill
我要他要我
And I want him to want me
但只是我,不是玛歌.嘉琳
But me, not Margo Channing
我都无法分辨清楚 他又怎么能?
And if I can't tell them apart, how can he?
为什么要分他和你呢?
Well, why should he and why should you?
比尔爱上玛歌.嘉琳
Bill's in love with Margo Channing
他被迫和她工作而爱上她
He's fought with her, worked with her, loved her
但十年后玛歌.嘉琳将会消失
But ten years from now Margo Channing will have ceased to exist
而剩下的将是什么?
And what's left will be What?
-玛歌,比尔只小你八岁
Margo, Bill is all of eight years younger than you
-我见多了那种勉强的婚姻
Those years stretch as the years go on I've seen it happen too often
-不会是你和比尔
Not to you, not to Bill
-他们不总是那么说吗?
Isn’t that what they always say?
他用走的,而汽车却不会动
I don't suppose the heater runs if the motor doesn't
很傻是吗?
Silly, isn't it?
他以为我们留在车内较暖和
You'd think they'd fix it so people could just sit in a car and keep warm
说到伊芙
About Eve
我的态度很不给她面子
I've acted pretty disgracefully toward her too
别为我找借口
-Well -Don't fumble for excuses
别在我放下头发的时候
Not here and now with my hair down
最好就说我太敏感了
At best, let's say I've been oversensitive to
事实上她那么年轻 柔弱而无助
Well, to the fact that she's so young, so feminine and so helpless
我想给比尔太多的东西
To so many things I want to be for Bill
女人的事业真是滑稽
It's funny, a woman's career
你为了爬得更快 而抛弃在楼梯上的东西
The things you drop on your way up so you can move faster
忘了当你又变回女人 会再需要它们
You forget you'll need them again when you get back to being a woman
不论喜不喜欢 每个女人的事业都会结束
That's one career all females have in common, whether we like it or not
成为一个女人
Being a woman
早晚我们都要做的
Sooner or later, we've got to work at it
不论我们有多渴望其它事业
No matter how many other careers we've had or wanted
但最后还是没什么好处 只能为人准备三餐
And in the last analysis, nothing's any good unless you can
铺床整被
look up just before dinner or
就是那样
turn around in bed and there he is
不那样就不是女人
Without that, you're not a woman
你会办公或收集书报
You're something with a French provincial office or a A book full of clippings
你不算是女人
But you're not a woman
布幕会慢慢放下
Slow curtain The end
玛歌!玛歌!我对这件事非常抱歉
Margo Margo, I want you to know how sorry I am about this
-对什么事? -这件事
-About what? -This
我说不出我心中的歉意
I can't tell you how sorry I am
别多想了,有些事命中注定
Don't give it a thought One of destiny's merry pranks
毕竟不是你把汽油弄光的
After all, you didn't personally drain the gasoline tank yourself
伊芙确实精彩无比
(Addison) Eve, of course, was superb
许多观众宁可再次
Many of the audience
来看玛歌演出
understandably preferred to return another time to see Margo
但那些长久留下的热烈喝采 是为伊芙
But those who remained cheered loudly, lustily and long for Eve
那个下午她非常周到 打电话邀我去
How thoughtful of her to call and invite me that afternoon
多么愉快的巧合
And what a happy coincidence that several representatives
刚好有几家报社代表也在场
of other newspapers happened to be present
那天下午我们都被邀请观赏
All of us invited that afternoon
一场候补的演出
to attend an understudy's performance,
对此管理人事先一概不知
about which the management knew nothing
直到9点才开幕
until they were forced to ring up the curtain at nine o'clock
很巧地
Coincidence
你不仅可以而且演出生动 你出色极了
(Bill) You were better than all right
还有一些毛病,不过没关系
You rang a bell Little things here and there, but it doesn't matter
你有权为自己感到骄傲
Be proud of yourself You've got a right to be
你为我感到骄傲吗?比尔
Are you proud of me, Bill?
-我承认我担心,有些怀疑
I admit I was worried when Max called I had my doubts
-你不该怀疑的 毕竟前天只是一个场景而已
-You shouldn't have had any doubts -After all, the other day was one scene
这个剧每一场景都令人激赏
The woods are full of one-scene sensations
你做到了 你努力和耐心,会成为好演员
But you did it With work and patience, you'll be a good actress
那是你的期望 -不也是你对我的期望吗?
-if that's what you wanna be -Is that what you want me to be?
-我在谈你和你的期望 我也是
-I'm talking about you and what you want -So am I
-我跟这个有何关系? -都有关系
-What have I got to do with it? -Everything
虽然我自找的,但与我无关 祝你幸运
The names I've been called, but never Svengali Good luck
比尔,别逃!
Don't run away, Bill
我要逃避什么?
From what would I be running?
-你在舞台上总是追求真实 那下了舞台呢?
You're always after truth on the stage What about off?
-我同样追求 那就面对它
-I'm for it -Then face it I have
我一直都是,自从第一晚在这间更衣室
Ever since that first night in here
当我告诉你 年轻女演员所该知道的?
I told you what every actress should know
当你告诉我不论我成为什么 都是因为你
You told me that whatever I became, it would be because of you
-化妆还是浓了点 -是为了你
-Make-up's a little heavy -And for you
-你很不简单 -你这么想吗?
-You're quite a girl -You think?
-我爱上玛歌,你没听说吗? -我全听说了
-I'm in love with Margo Hadn't you heard? -You hear all kinds of things
我只是个凡人,为合约才投入 而好奇的是另外一个人
I'm only human, rumors to the contrary, and I'm as curious as the next man
-试试看吧! -只是…
-Find out -Only thing:
我追求的是我想要追求的
what I go after I want to go after
我不要别人跟着我
I don't want it to come after me
别哭! 你有你值得骄傲的地方
Don't cry Just score it as an incomplete forward pass
是谁?
Who is it?
我可以进来吗?
May I come in?
当然可以,杜维特先生
Certainly, Mr DeWitt
我如愿见到剧院聚集大群 为你疯狂的观众
I expected to find this room with a theatreful of people at your feet
我很幸运他们没有丢东西 -你的表演我一点也不意外
-I'm lucky they didn't throw things -Your performance was no surprise to me
经过上次,我认为诺言 必然会实现
After the other day, I regarded it as simply a promise fulfilled
你太仁慈了 但依然是嘉琳小姐主演
You're more than kind But it's still Miss Channing's performance
我只是她的影子而已 你却没看到真正的她
I'm the carbon copy you read when you can't find the original
你太谦虚了 -不是谦虚 我只是想跟自己开个玩笑
-You're more than modest -It's not modesty I don't try to kid myself
若你愿意听我建议有一种
A revolutionary approach to the theatre
革命性打进戏剧界的方法 -请说
-But if I may make a suggestion -Please do
我认为该是你享有人情味时
I think the time has come to shed some of your humility
适当的表现是绝对有必要的
It is just as false not to blow your horn at all as it is to blow it too loudly
我目的并不在表现自己
I don't think I've done anything to sound off about
我们来到世上绝不是想 默默无闻
We come into this world with our little egos equipped with individual horns
若我们不自我表现 还有谁会呢?
If we don't blow them, who else will?
即使如此 一次漂亮的替代演出 明天就会被遗忘的
Even so One pretty good performance by an understudy, it'll be forgotten tomorrow
不一定要那样
It needn't be
即使我像你说的,不要谦卑 自夸一下,
Even if I wanted to, as you say, be less humble, blow my own horn,
我要怎么做呢? 我是个默默无闻的人
how would I do it? I'm less than nobody
-我来头就不小 -你当然是
-I'm somebody -You certainly are
让门开着,我们可以谈话
Leave the door open a bit, so we can talk
你先换衣服 如果没什么其它的事 我们一起吃顿晚餐
After you change, if you're not busy elsewhere, we could have supper
我很乐意,干嘛假装很忙呢?
I'd love to Or should I pretend I'm busy?
让我们彼此坦诚相对 我想为你作一栏报导
Let's have a minimum of pretending I shall want to do a column about you
-我的事连一段都写不满
I'm not even enough for a paragraph
-或许不只一栏
Perhaps more than one
我很想听听有关你的事 我零星听过你一些事
There's so much I want to know I've heard your story in part
你家在威斯康辛 有个悲惨的婚姻
Your home in Wisconsin, your tragic marriage,
你对玛歌的狂热依恋
your fanatical attachment to Margo
那是从旧金山开始的,是吗?
It started in San Francisco, didn't it?
我说你崇拜玛歌是从 旧金山开始的,是吗?
I say your idolatry of Margo started in San Francisco, didn't it?
没错!
That's right
旧金山,加州的文化之都
San Francisco, an oasis of civilization in the California desert
你同意我对旧金山的观点吗?
Tell me, do you share my high opinion of San Francisco?
是的,我同意
Yes, I do
玛歌首次在台上吸引你 注意的夜晚
And that memorable night when Margo first dazzled you from the stage,
那是旧金山哪家剧院? 是舒伯特剧院吗?
what theatre was it in San Francisco? Was it the Shubert?
是的,舒伯特剧院
Yes, the Shubert
舒伯特,最后的剧场 充满了传统
Fine old theatre, the Shubert Full of tradition
未遭受地震侵袭 该说是火灾
Untouched by the earthquake Or should I say fire?
告诉我你先生叫什么名字?
Tell me, what was your husband's name?
-艾迪 -艾迪什么?
-Eddie -Eddie what?
我要去淋浴了 我会听不见你说的话
I'm about to go into the shower I won't be able to hear you
我可以等
Well, it can wait
-你想去哪里?今晚蛮特别的
Where would you like to go? We must make this a special night
-由你安排
You take charge
我会的
I believe I will
几家早报专栏刊载伊芙演出
(Karen) Some morning papers carried a squib about Eve's performance
内容不多,但全是赞美
Not much, but full of praise
我无法想象他们怎么知道的
I couldn't imagine how they found out about it
但罗维说麦斯负责宣传 可能把消息散出去
But Lloyd said Max's publicity man probably sent out the story
不论如何我深深的感到 罪恶和愧疚
At any rate, I felt terribly guilty and ashamed of myself
我只想忘掉这一切
and wanted nothing so much as to forget the whole thing
玛歌和我在21号午餐
Margo and I were having lunch at 21,
就像朋友般,那天阳光普照
just like girlfriends, with hats on
-嘉琳小姐来了吗? -还没,瑞奇太太
-Has Miss Channing come in? -Not yet
-谢谢
Thank you
伊芙,听说你演出非常成功
Oh, Eve! I've heard the most wonderful things about your performance
-大概是事先大伙套好的吧!
Relief that I managed to stagger through it
-她太出色了
She was magnificent
-你也听到了-我在那里,我亲眼见到
-Then you've heard, too -I was there
-你昨晚去看演出了? －纯粹是巧合
-You were at the play last night? -A happy coincidence
-我们和一个天才电影观察家吃午餐 -真会利用时间
-We're having lunch with a talent scout -They certainly don't waste much time
没什么,我们只吃午餐
-It's nothing definite Just lunch -They'll be wasting their time
如果他们料到伊芙根本 不想去好莱坞
Eve has no intention of going to Hollywood
从你的穿着看来 我猜和你进餐的是位小姐
By your smart dress, I take it your companion is a lady?
玛歌! －玛歌到公共场合午餐?
-Margo -Margo lunching in public?
是个新的玛歌 只不过她如往常一样迟到
It's a new Margo, but she's just as late as the old one
或许她为新的原因迟到吧!
She may be later than you think
不妨读我的专栏消磨时间
Why not read my column to pass the time?
-时间会过得快些 -谢谢!艾德生
-The minutes will fly like hours -Thank you, Addison
我们必须去参加音乐演奏会了
Now we must join our sunburned eager beaver
-再见,凯伦 -再见
-Goodbye, Karen -Goodbye
多年以来我看过这么多演出 真叫我听烦了
"And so my hat which has, lo, these many seasons,
直到哈林顿小姐出现
"become firmly rooted about my ears, is lifted to Miss Harrington
我又再度在街上舞蹈 在屋顶上欢呼
"I am available for dancing in the streets and shouting from the housetops "
这真是太虚伪了吧! 看这里,看这里,听着
I thought that one went out with Woollcott Now listen to this
哈林顿小姐优点太多 足以出一部书
"Miss Harrington had much to tell and these columns shall report her faithfully
本栏将忠实为其报导 她在戏剧上出色的表现
"about the lamentable practice in our theatre of permitting
或容我以成熟的诠释技巧 来继续扮演此角色
"mature actresses to continue playing roles
需要这年轻且充满活力 来使演出永留观众记忆里
"requiring a youth and vigor of which they retain but a dim memory "
-我真不相信 -还有更精彩的
-I just can't believe it -It gets better
我们了解舞台应面临换血
"About the understandable reluctance of our entrenched first ladies of the stage
该鼓励像哈林顿一样的年轻演员
"to encourage, shall we say, younger actresses,
长期争取演出机会
"and Miss Harrington's unsupported struggle for opportunity "
我真不敢相信他说那种话 －这个鼠辈说每个人犯了
-I can't believe Eve said those things -In this rat race,
阻碍文化进步的罪
everybody's guilty till proved innocent
剧院和文化有何差距?
One of the differences between the theatre and civilization
令我奇怪的是
What gets me
为何城里报纸 全都注意到那种特别的演出?
is how all the papers happened to catch that particular performance
罗维说是宣传部发出的
Lloyd says it's a publicity release
那小女巫一定派出印第安武士
The witch must have sent out Indian Runners,
到酒吧,蒸气房和博物馆 她所能取得支持的地方
snatching critics out of bars, steam rooms and museums or wherever they hole up
我绝不会轻易放过她
She won't get away with it
艾德生绝不会称心如意
Nor will Addison DeWitt and his poison pen
如果我的律师不采取行动
If Equity or my lawyer can't or won't do anything about it,
我会亲自把那下流的 杜维特先生勒死
I shall personally stuff that pathetic little lost lamb down Mr DeWitt's ugly throat!
我阅读完那篇东西 就马上赶来了
I came as soon as I read that piece of filth I ran all the way
比尔在这里,宝贝!
Bill's here, baby
一切都会没事的
Everything's all right now
我想此刻就是法国人说的 祸从天降
I guess at this point I'm what the French call "de trop "
或许没那么严重
Maybe just a little around the edges
艾德生从头到尾导演这一幕
It's Addison from start to finish It drips with his brand of venom
利用那小女孩,扭曲她的话
Taking advantage of a kid, twisting her words,
让她说他想写的话
making her say what he wanted her to say
-你哪里得来这消息的? -伊芙!
-Where did you get all that information? -Eve
-伊芙? -她来看过我
-Eve? -She's been to see me
事实上你进来时,她刚走 你刚好错过了
She left just before you came in You just missed her
太可惜了 －想解释访问的事
-That was a pity -Wanted to explain about the interview
想找某人道歉 她不敢面对玛歌
Wanted to apologize to someone, and didn't dare face Margo
她为何不敢呢? 她一开口就无法控制
-I wonder why -She started talking and couldn't finish
哭得好伤心
She cried so
我查过我们的财务状况 若你让我说明
I've been going over our financial position, if you'll pardon the expression
你的话题转得太快! 就要缴税金了
-That's quite a change of subject -What with taxes coming up, and,
因为我是个编剧 不是个精算师,我一直在想
since I'm a playwright and not an oil-well operator, I was thinking
我努力在听你说
I'm trying hard to follow you
伊芙要等到下一季,才能上台 表演
Instead of waiting until next season to do Footsteps on the Ceiling,
那是很好的安排
which is in pretty good shape,
如果可说服玛歌跟 艾吉和伍德作巡回演出
and if Margo can be talked into going on tour with Aged in Wood,
我们可马上开始制作
we could put Footsteps into production right away
我开始有点明白了 －若能恰当处理就行得通
-I'm beginning to catch up -If we can cast it properly, that is
或许找个年轻的演那角色
Maybe get some younger actress?
某个适合演那个角色的人
Someone who'd look the part as well as play it?
你得承认这是个新奇构想 －是你想出的或是伊芙提的
-You've got to admit, it'd be a novelty -Now you're quoting Addison or Eve
伊芙没提到戏,只是提一下
Eve did mention the play, but in passing
她从没要求角色 她没那种勇气
She'd never have the nerve to ask to play a part like Cora
伊芙甚至会要求 让她演加丝黛萝
Eve would ask Abbott to give her Costello
不!那是我自己的意思 当她跟我谈到剧的时候
I got the idea myself while she was talking about the play
当然只是暗示了
-With gestures, of course -To write something
这次我写的是完全可靠的角色 而且我总算不必妥协了
and have it realized completely For once, not to compromise
罗维 瑞奇你不会是想把那角色
Lloyd Richards, do not consider
给那卑鄙的小坏虫
giving that contemptible little worm the part of Cora!
等等! 这些年来玛歌.嘉琳并没有一直要你迁就她
-Now just a minute -Margo's not been exactly a compromise
就算能完成美好的作品 妥协又算什么呢?
Playwrights everywhere would give their shirts for that compromise
你给我等一下
Now just a minute
真叫人震惊,伊芙既不忠实 又卑鄙,这是会传染的
Eve's disloyalty and ingratitude must be contagious
你这种莫名的歇斯底里
All this hysteria because of an impulsive excited kid
就为一个纯真的孩子被专业 主观的剧评家杜维特唆使
and a professional manure-slinger named DeWitt
她道歉了,不是吗? 我相信她还下跪,很感人
-She apologized, didn't she? -On her knees, I've no doubt
也非常戏剧化的艺术
Very touching Very Academy of Dramatic Arts
你那付刻薄相 就因为我不符合你的要求
That bitter cynicism is something you've acquired since you left Radcliffe
我今天的刻薄是因为我发现 我和一个小男孩有很大距离
That cynicism I acquired the day I discovered I was different from little boys
哈啰!
Hello
嘿!玛歌!
Oh, hi, Margo
不!不一点也不!
No, not at all
凯伦和我正在聊天
Karen and I were just chatting
当然可以,而且我们很乐意
Yes, I'm sure we can and I'm sure we'd love to
对,11点45分
Right 11 45ish
好,到时见
See you then
玛歌和比尔要我们收工后 到饭店的酒吧跟他们喝酒
Margo and Bill want us to meet them at the Cub Room tonight after the theatre
玛歌.嘉琳会在酒吧间
Margo Channing in the Cub Room
我真意外,她心情好转了
I couldn't be more surprised if she'd said Grant's tomb
很高兴比尔回心转意了 他们失去对方会活不下去
-I'm glad Bill's back -They'd die without each other
达令!我没给伊芙任何承诺 我只觉得她很适合那角色
I didn't promise Eve anything I said she'd be fine for the part
但仍有些困难
but there were practical difficulties
例如什么? 你是其中原因之一
-Such as? -You, for one
我告诉你安排玛歌演那角色 没有你许可,我不会换人
I told her you wanted Margo to play the part and I would want your approval
那就好!太好了!
That's fine Fine and dandy
往后伊芙.哈林顿小姐 有任何要求都来找我
Just refer all of Miss Eve Harrington's future requests to me
所谓演技并非那么遥不可及
The so-called art of acting is not one for which I have a particularly high regard
听!听! －不过你们可以引述下面的话
-Hear, hear -But you may quote me as follows
今晚玛歌.嘉琳小姐 演出的精彩好戏
"Tonight Miss Margo Channing gave a performance in your cockamamie play,
演技是我前所未见 我期望能再次大饱眼福
"the like of which I have never seen before and expect rarely to see again "
-他并非吹嘘我很不错 -你太出色了
-He does not exaggerate I was good -You were great
真是美好的夜晚 你该给你候补演员 哈林顿小姐一个通告
Quite a night I hear your understudy, a Miss Harrington, has given her notice
-太糟了 -我为此难过
-Too bad -I'm broken up about it
为某些理由让你无法举杯庆祝
You just can't pick up champagne and drink it
该有人聪明地来个干杯
Somebody's got to be very witty about a toast
我请你干杯,
I shall propose the toast,
不是说笑 是诚心诚意
without wit, with all my heart
-玛歌
To Margo
-为我未来的新娘干杯 -荣耀的哈利路亚
-To my bride-to-be -Glory hallelujah
-玛歌 -喝吧!
-Margo -Drink
什么时候?你们何时结婚? -明天十点我们在市政府见
-When? When are you going to do it? -Tomorrow we meet at City Hall at ten
你一定要准时 -当然
-And you're going to be on time -Yes, sir
市政府!那上报不太光彩
City Hall, that's for prizefighters and reporters
我看到大教堂吧! 有主教加上整排的鲜花
I see a cathedral, banks of flowers
这只是为了结婚证书 还要三天等验血及一些手续
It's only for the license There's a three-day wait for blood tests
若你根本没有血 我也会嫁你
I'll marry you if it turns out you have no blood at all
你打算穿什么? 简单点就行了
-What are you going to wear? -Something simple,
晚礼服外加貂皮大衣
a fur coat over a nightgown
在卡希路包尔公园的教堂
The point is this In a cathedral, a ballpark or a penny arcade,
我们请两位观礼 -你们是我们最亲密的朋友
we want you two beside us, as our nearest and dearest friends
-我们是,我们永远都是
Which we are Which we'll always be
人生少有这么美好的时刻 值得永记在心
There are very few moments in life as good as this Let's remember it
敬每一位和我们全体 我们从没这么亲近过
To each of us and all of us, never have we been more close
愿我们永远如此
May we never be farther apart
-瑞奇太太 -什么事?
-Mrs Richards? -Yes
-你的 -谢谢
-For you -Thank you
太不谨慎了,这样就能打开
Very indiscreet A note in the open like that
下次叫你情人要封紧点
Next time, tell your lover to blow smoke rings or tap a glass
罗维,我要你别计较这个
Lloyd, I want you to be big about this
今晚世界充满了爱 每一个女人都很危险
The world is full of love tonight No woman is safe
这真是创世界的纪录
Well, this beats all world's records for running, jumping or standing gall
“请原谅,打扰你们愉快聚餐
"Forgive my butting in to what seems such a happy occasion,
但我有要事想和你谈”
"but it's important that I speak with you
“请…”还有下划线
"'Please"' and that's underlined,
“请到女化妆室见面,伊芙”
"meet me in the ladies' room Eve "
我知道她在那里当候补演员
I understand she's now the understudy in there
把那支空瓶给我 我可能会找到他们
Hand me that empty bottle I may find her
看!混蛋在那儿
Well, look There's Rasputin
打开香槟
Encore du champagne
-还要香槟?嘉琳小姐 -我已经说过了,鲍伯
-More champagne, Miss Channing? -That's what I said, bub
也许她只想道歉
Maybe she just wants to apologize
我对她要说的 一点也不感兴趣
I have no interest in anything she may say
-她能说什么?我很感兴趣
But what could she say? That's what fascinates me
-去查清楚 凯伦,凭我们多年的友谊
-Go on, find out -Karen, in all the years of our friendship,
我绝不让你独自进化妆室
I have never let you go to the ladies' room alone
但现在我得让你去
Now I must I am busting to find out
我渴望查出那颗发烧小脑袋 在想些什么
what's going on in that feverish little brain waiting in there
好吧! 好吧!
Well All right
凯伦,
Karen!
太好了
How nice
很有效,但为什么对着我呢?
Very effective, but why take it out on me?
我还在想你会不会来
I was wondering whether you'd come at all
别站起来,我可不是皇太后
Don't get up And don't act as if I were the Queen Mother
-我没想到你会不高兴
I don't expect you to be pleasant
-我本来就不高兴
I don't intend to be
我们能坐下来谈一分钟吗? 我有许多不易启齿的话要说
Can't we sit down just for a minute? I've got a lot to say and none of its easy
-不可能太多的 -事实上是的
-There can't be very much -But there is
-不管容不容易,我都不相信 -你该相信的
-Easy or not, I won't believe a word of it -Why should you?
请坐
Please sit down
我一向自认为很聪明 精明,
You know, I've always considered myself a very clever girl
我的头脑很灵光
Smart, good head on my shoulders, that sort of thing
绝不会弄错场合说错话
Never the wrong word at the wrong time
那我就不会遇上艾德生了
But then I'd never met Addison DeWitt
我记得有一次我去试演
I remember I had a tooth pulled once
他们给我几个候补机会 我不记得名字了
They gave me some anaesthetic I don't remember the name
那对我产生奇怪的影响
It affected me strangely
我发现自己说些没想过的话
I found myself saying things I wasn't even thinking
好像我的意识跑出我体外 无法控制自己的言语及行为
As if my mind was outside of my body and couldn't control what I did or said
-你就是那样跟艾德生说的? -就是那样
-And you felt like that talking to Addison? -In a way
你努力想说出内心的话
You find yourself trying to say what you mean,
但话却变了,
but somehow the words change
变成他的话
They become his words
突然间你说的不是你的意思 或他的意思
And suddenly you're not saying what you mean, but what he means
你要我相信你没说那些话
Do you expect me to believe that you didn't say any of that?
而那全是艾德生说的吗?
That they were all Addison?
我并不期望你相信
I don't expect you to believe anything,
-只是责任与耻辱都在于我
except that the responsibility is mine, and the disgrace
-我们别再演戏了
Let's not get overdramatic
你真的很看不起我
You really have a low opinion of me, haven't you?
我给你一些愉快的消息
I'll give you some pleasant news
我在城里到处遭冷眼
I've been told off in no uncertain terms, all over town
嘉琳应该很高兴听到这个
Miss Channing should be happy to hear that
知道她的朋友多么忠实
To know how loyal her friends are,
而我比她想象的更忠实
how much more loyal than she had a right to expect me to be
-伊芙,不要哭 -我没哭
-Eve, don't cry -I'm not crying
告诉我 你和好莱坞那个人午餐 结果如何?
Tell me, how did your luncheon turn out with the man from Hollywood?
他答应我做几次试镜
Some vague promises of a test
会有个特别角色给我
If a particular part should come along, one of those things
-但他们很重视你的演出 -候补的演出
-But the raves about your performance -An understudy's performance
我想你太夸张了
Well, I think you're painting the picture a little blacker than it is, really
若没其它办法,别低估了他 你有个很有势力的朋友
Don't underestimate him You have a powerful friend in Addison
-他不是我朋友,你才是
He's not my friend You were my friends
-他可以帮你 -但愿我没遇见他
-He can help you -I wish I'd never met him
真希望他死
I'd like him to be dead
我希望我的朋友回来
I want my friends back
伊芙! 我不认为你故意那么做的
Eve I don't think you meant to cause unhappiness
但是你做了 或许你也不太好过
But you did More to yourself perhaps, as it turned out, than to anyone else
-我永远无法释怀 -你会的
-I'll never get over it -Oh, yes, you will
新剧院将重新建起 在舞台上没有永远不变的事
You theatre people always do Nothing is forever in the theatre
不论呈现什么 火光闪烁,火焰汹涌
Whatever it is, it's here, it flares up, burns hot,
它消失了
and it's gone
-但愿我能相信 -给你自己时间吧!
-I wish I could believe that -Give yourself time
别太担心人们的想法
Don't worry too much about what people think
你很年轻,很有才华
You're very young and very talented
信不信由你 我帮不上忙了
And, believe it or not, if there's anything I can do
有件事你能
There is something
我知道 一件你能做的最重要的事
-I think I know -Something most important you can do
你想演蔻拉 你要我告诉罗维 把那角色给你演
You wanna play Cora You want me to tell Lloyd I think you should play it
假如你这么告诉他 他会把这角色给我
If you told him so, he'd give me the part He said he would
你终于说出来了 你不知道那角色 是为玛歌写的吗?
After all you've said Don't you know that part was written for Margo?
15年前可能是 但现在该是我的角色
It might've been 15 years ago It's my part now
你的口气就像艾德生的文章 蔻拉是我的角色,你一定要 告诉罗维给我那角色
-You talk just as Addison said you did -Cora is my part You've got to tell Lloyd
-没有任何原因能让我那么说
Nothing in the world will make me say that
-艾德生要我演那个角色
Addison wants me to play it
-除非我死了 -我看不需要的
-Over my dead body -That won't be necessary
艾德生知道玛歌 刚好赶不上演出
Addison knows how Margo happened to miss that performance,
我怎会知道她没赶上 而通知城里每家报社
how I happened to know she'd miss it in time to notify every paper in town
经过非常曲折 艾德生可制造许多故事
It's quite a story Addison could make quite a thing of it
想象他多么邪恶
Imagine how snide and vicious he could get,
利用那些事虚造声势
and still tell nothing but the truth
我必须先跟你谈
I had a time persuading him
你最好坐下,你脸色很苍白
You better sit down You look a bit wobbly
如果我演蔻拉 艾德生绝不会将真相说出来
If I play Cora, Addison will never tell what happened, in or out of print
彼此简单的交换好处
A simple exchange of favors
我很高兴终于能帮你忙
I'm so happy I can do something for you at long last
你和玛歌
Your friendship with Margo,
交情深厚
your deep, close friendship
若她知道你所玩的奸计
What would happen to it
会如何呢?
if she knew the cheap trick you played on her for my benefit?
你和罗维能在影剧圈混多久
You and Lloyd, how long, even in the theatre,
大家才会忘掉你们所做的事 而不再相信你们
before people forgot what happened and trusted you again?
不能这样
No
让大家注意蔻拉由谁演出 要轻松多了
It would be so much easier for everyone concerned if I were to play Cora
对剧院也好多了
So much better theatre, too
剧中的角色
A part in a play
你这么做只为争取这角色
You'd do all that just for a part in a play?
我会尽力争取更多的角色
I'd do much more for a part that good
饿吗?
Hungry?
我绝不意外,你的哀兵之计
I'm not surprised, after all that humble pie
没那回事 凯伦和我相谈甚欢
Nothing of the kind Karen and I had a nice talk
女人之间坦诚相见
Heart to heart? Woman to woman?
包括闲聊你希望演蔻拉一角?
Including a casual reference to the part of Cora and your hopes of playing it?
我很坦白地和她讨论
I discussed it very openly
我告诉她我和罗维讲了 他很感兴趣
I told her I'd spoken to Lloyd, and that he was interested
凯伦当然说那角色 预备由玛歌演出
And Karen mentioned, of course, that Margo expects to play the part?
奇怪!她一直没提玛歌
Oddly enough, she didn't say a word about Margo
只是她说很乐意促成 我演那个角色
Just that she'll be happy to do what she can to see that I play it
真是那样吗?
Just like that, eh?
就是那样!
Just like that
知道吗?伊芙 有时候我觉得你有事瞒着我
You know, Eve, sometimes I think you keep things from me
-你这句话并不好笑 -本来就不好笑
-I don't think that's funny -It wasn't meant to be
你是我认识的最值得信赖的人
I confide in you and rely on you more than anyone I've ever known
却没头没脑的说那种话
To say a thing like that now, without any reason,
而我现在比以往更需要你
when I need you more than ever
希望你说的是真心话
I hope you mean what you say
我打算好好与你相处
I intend to hold you to it
看来我们有许多共同点
We have a great deal in common, it seems to me
怎么了? 没什么,她含着泪说抱歉
-Well, what happened? -Nothing much She apologized
-含着泪? -是的
-With tears? -With tears
-但不是马上落泪 首先她一定抬着头 说了一大套道理
But not right away First fight them back, chin up, stout fellow
-对了! -很有水准,技术也很高明
-Check -Very classy Lots of technique
这么久她就只是向你道歉 那你说了什么?
You mean all this time she's done nothing but apologize? What did you say?
没说什么
Not much
-新郎,我可要个结婚礼物吗?
Groom, may I have a wedding present?
-你要什么?德州吗? 我要大家别再谈伊芙
-What would you like? Texas? -I want everybody to shut up about Eve
绝口别再提伊芙 我就要这个
Just shut up about Eve That's all I want
再给凯伦倒些酒
Give Karen more wine
我从没这么快乐过
Never have I been so happy
这房间真的很棒 酒吧屋,
Isn't it a lovely room? The Cub Room
真是个好名字 来的都是些主角人物
What a lovely, clever name Where the elite meet
我从没看过这么多大人物 注意着我
Never have I seen so much elite, all with their eyes on me,
好让我用瓶子打他鼻子
waiting for me to crack that little gnome on the noggin with a bottle
但不是今晚,今晚我宽恕一切 连伊芙在内,我宽恕伊芙
But not tonight I'm forgiving tonight Even Eve I forgive Eve
他们走了
There they go
伊芙也走了
There goes Eve
伊芙?魔鬼?她是小恶魔
Eve Evil, little Miss Evil
魔鬼都做什么? 他们都干什么?
But "the evil that men do " How does that go, groom?
他们会留下好的吗?
Something about the good they leave behind
我曾演过一次老式的魔鬼
I played it once in rep in Wilkes-Barre
你在里头也没得到什么好处
You've got it backwards, even for Wilkes-Barre
知道我为何原谅伊芙吗? 她留下了好东西
Do you know why I forgive Eve? She left good behind
因此我们四人会在此聚会 是伊芙的错,我原谅她
The four of us here together, it's Eve fault I forgive her
还有比尔,尤其是比尔 也是她促成的
And Bill, especially Bill She did that too
-或许她一点也没什么恶意
You know, she probably means well after all
-她是个讨厌鬼 -谁都骗不了玛歌的
-She is a louse -Never try to outguess Margo
-比尔 -什么事?
-Groom? -Yes, dear
-知道我要当什么吗? -牛仔?
-Do you know what I'm going to be? -A cowboy?
-结婚的女人 需要一纸结婚证书
-A married lady -With a paper to prove it
我会期待着六点的来临 等待丈夫回家
I'm going to look up at six o'clock, and there he'll be
-记得吧!凯伦 -我记得
-Remember, Karen? -I remember
-你会在那里吧! -我绝不放弃那种特权
-You'll be there, won't you? -Often enough to keep the franchise
绝没有自动退出舞台的
No more make-believe, offstage or on
记得吗?罗维,我需要退休了
Remember, Lloyd? I mean it now
-罗维,你保证不生我的气吗?
Lloyd, will you promise not to be angry with me?
-那要看情形 -我是指真正的生气
-That depends -No, I mean deeply angry
-我想我不会的
I don't think I could be
-我不想演蔻拉
Well, I don't want to play Cora
-什么? 等等,你总是那么容易激动
-What? -You're always so touchy about his plays
那个角色是个很棒的角色 剧本也很好,但不适合我了
It isn't the part It's a great part and a fine play But not for me anymore
不再适合一个想安定下来 过平淡生活的结婚女性
Not for a foursquare, upright, downright, forthright, married lady
那和结婚有何关系?
What's your being married got to do with it?
那意谓我终于找到自己的生活
It means I've finally got a life to live
不用再演过于年轻的角色
I don't have to play parts I'm too old for
就只为消磨无所事事的夜晚
just because I've got nothing to do with my nights
罗维,我知道你已弄好计划 相信我会补偿你
Oh, Lloyd, I'll make it up to you, believe me
为这角色忙了一年 我只能请你谅解
I'll tour a year with this one, anything Only you do understand, don't you?
-什么事那么好笑? -没事
-What's so funny? -Nothing
-没事? -一切都太好笑了
-Nothing? -Everything Everything's so funny
罗维从没问过我
(Karen) Lloyd never got around to asking
是否愿意让伊芙演蔻拉一角
whether it was all right with me for Eve to play Cora
很奇怪首先比尔拒绝导演此剧 因为伊芙参加演出
Bill, oddly enough, refused to direct the play at first, with Eve in it
罗维和麦斯最后说服了他
Lloyd and Max finally won him over
玛歌从没到排演现场
Margo never came to rehearsal
她说家事太忙了
"Too much to do around the house," she said
我从不知道比尔和罗维 会如此激烈争吵
I'd never known Bill and Lloyd to fight as bitterly and often,
都是因伊芙惹的祸
and always over some business for Eve,
为了她的动作或她台词
or a move, or the way she read a speech
我从不知道罗维如此 不尊重比尔的导演
But I'd never known Lloyd to meddle as much with Bill's directing,
只要一牵涉到伊芙便会如此
as far as it affected Eve, that is
然而伊芙说服他们继续下去
Somehow Eve kept them going
比尔退让,罗维似乎很高兴
Bill stuck it out Lloyd seemed happy
我想我最好别再参与排演
And I thought it might be best if I skipped rehearsals from then on
我感觉好像能预知它会发生 而它真的发生
It seemed to me I had known always that it would happen And here it was
我感到无助 巨大的无助感使我无计可施
I felt helpless That helplessness you feel when you have no talent to offer,
除了对丈夫的爱
outside of loving your husband
我如何去竞争 罗维一切都依赖我
How could I compete? Everything Lloyd loved about me,
他长时间以来都习惯如此
he'd gotten used to long ago
哈啰!
Hello?
谁? 谁要找瑞奇先生?
Who? Who's calling Mr Richards?
我的名字并不重要 我住在哈林顿小姐对面
My name wouldn't mean anything I room across the hall from Eve Harrington
她身体不适,哭了整晚 就只有低泣,
She isn't well She's been crying all night and she's hysterical
不去看医生
She doesn't want a doctor and
那是谁?有什么事?
Who is it? What's it all about?
哈林顿小姐叫你 打电话给瑞奇先生吗? 没有,她没叫我打电话
-Did Miss Harrington tell you to call? -Oh, no Eve didn't say to call him
我记得见过瑞奇先生 和她一起几次
I saw Mr Richards with her a couple of times
我想他们是好朋友
I thought, they being such good friends
哈啰!我是罗维瑞奇 她在哪里?让我跟她说话
This is Lloyd Richards Where is Eve? Let me talk to her
你好,瑞奇先生 她在楼上房间
Hello, Mr Richards She's upstairs in her room
我实在不愿这样打扰你 但伊芙的状况
I really hate to bother you this way, but the way Eve's been feeling,
我耽心她的病 明天可能不能演出了
I've been worried sick, what with her leaving tomorrow for New Haven
叫她别耽心,我马上过去
Tell her not to worry Tell her I'll be right over
对戏剧界而言 康乃迪克州的新天堂…
(Addison) To the theatre world, New Haven, Connecticut,
是舒伯特剧院和塔夫饭店间 的一条短短人行道
is a short stretch of sidewalk between the Shubert Theatre and the Taft Hotel,
被商店重重包围像座小城市
surrounded by what looks very much like a small city
这里的经理称它为出城的门
It is here that managers have what are called out-of-town openings,
它是供那些纽约人 想出城用的
which are openings for New Yorkers who want to go out of town
多美好的一天 像是在天堂般
What a day What a heavenly day
诺曼底登陆日 -说得是
-D-day -Just like it
明早你会觉得
Tomorrow morning, you will have won your beachhead
人终归要死的
on the shores of immortality
你专栏里最吸引人的描述
Stop rehearsing your column
实在很怪
Isn’t it strange, Addison?
我觉得很恐慌,想逃避他们
I thought I'd be panic-stricken, want to run away or something
一直不想等待夜晚的降临 怕到手了又失掉
Instead, I can't wait for tonight to come To come and go
你对明日那么肯定吗?
Are you that sure of tomorrow?
-你不是吗? -坦白说,是的
-Aren't you? -Frankly, yes
将是个永生难忘的一夜
It'll be a night to remember
我终于梦想成真
It'll bring me everything I've ever wanted
-旧旅程结束,新旅程开始
The end of an old road, the beginning of a new one
-旅途上铺满钻石和黄金?-你对我的了解不只那样
-All paved with diamonds and gold? -You know me better than that
-追求新战利品
Paved with what, then?
没错
Stars
几点了?
What time?
才四点而已
Almost four
有足够时间可长睡一下
Plenty of time for a nice, long nap
我昨晚睡得不好
We rehearsed most of last night
-你现在可以睡得着吗?
You could sleep now, couldn't you?
-有何不可? 杰出的冷血杀手
-Why not? -The mark of a true killer
安然熟睡, 再出来战斗
Sleep tight, rest easy and come out fighting
你为何叫我杀手?
Why did you call me a killer?
我说杀手意思指冠军 我用了我的拳击术语
Did I say killer? I meant champion I get my boxing terms mixed
艾德生,进来几分钟好吗?
Addison, come in for a minute, will you?
我有件事要告诉你
I've got something to tell you
很美但很贵的酒 这不会太奢侈吗?
Suites are for expense accounts You're being extravagant
麦斯买的 他和罗维有喝酒习惯 不过罗维坚持要买
Max is paying for it He and Lloyd had a terrific row, but Lloyd insisted
你想喝酒吗? 那么说是强迫中奖的啰!
-Can I fix you a drink? -With the reluctant compliments of Max?
是罗维,我没有这种嗜好
Lloyd I never have any
我们收工后,他喜欢喝几杯 所以装这组酒
He likes a few drinks after we finish, so he sent it up
真有情调 罗维一定一心想把你棒上天
Some plain soda Lloyd must be expecting a record run in New Haven
一半是为了今晚 你也在邀请之列
That's for tonight You're invited
我们邀请所有参加演出的人
We're having everyone up after the performance
-我们吗?
"We are?"
-罗维和我
Lloyd and I
-我发现这情况对凯伦很不利
I find it odd that Karen isn't here for the opening
-艾德生 你对罗维用情
-Addison -She was always so devoted to Lloyd
不觉得会深深伤害凯伦吗?
One would think only death could keep her
艾德生
Addison
我说这将是永生难忘的一夜 我心中所有愿望终于成真
I said this would be a night to remember, that it would bring me all I ever wanted
对,旧旅程结束
Oh, yes Something about an old road ending
而新旅途开始
and a new one starting, all paved with stars
-我指的不仅是戏剧
I didn't mean just the theatre
-还有什么?
What else?
罗维 瑞奇
Lloyd Richards
他将离开凯伦 我们要结婚了
He's going to leave Karen We're going to be married
是那么回事,罗维
So that's it Lloyd
终究还是在演戏
Still just the theatre, after all
没有其它目的
It's nothing of the kind
罗维爱我 我爱他
Lloyd loves me I love him
我不了解罗维和他的爱
I know nothing of Lloyd's loves
也不想去了解,但我很了解你
I leave those to Louisa May Alcott But I know you
我和罗维相爱
I'm in love with Lloyd
在美国罗维 瑞奇是 最成功的商业剧作家
He is a commercially successful playwright
你无权说这种话 技术上那真是前途看好
-You have no right to say that -And, artistically, very promising
亲爱的伊芙,这对象该是我
Eve, dear, this is Addison
艾德生,那不是很完美吗?
Oh, Addison, won't it be just perfect?
罗维和我 -我们未来发展真是无可限量
Lloyd and I There's no telling how far we can go
他会为我写伟大的作品 我会使那些剧作不朽
He'll write great plays for me I'll make them great
除了罗维和我之外 我只告诉你一个人
You're the only one who knows, except Lloyd and me
-还有凯伦 -她不知道
-And Karen -She doesn't know
-她很清楚知道他不会来 -并不完全了解
-She knows enough not to be here -But not all of it
她不知道罗维和我要结婚了 -我明白了
-Not that Lloyd and I are gonna be married -I see
你们何时最后一次见面?
And when was this unholy alliance joined?
我们前天晚上决定的 在我们到这里之前
We decided night before last, before we came up here
我相信当时情景 一定很罗曼蒂克
I trust the setting was properly romantic
淡淡的烛光,舞台上有 吉普赛小提琴的演奏
Lights on dimmers and gypsy violins offstage
情景并不罗曼蒂克
The setting wasn't romantic,
不过罗维却是
but Lloyd was
他清晨三点来这里敲我的门
He woke me up at three o'clock in the morning, banging on my door
说他睡不着 他离开凯伦
He couldn't sleep, he said He'd left Karen
无法再写剧本 除非我答应嫁给他
Couldn't go on with the play or anything else until I promised to marry him
我们不断的谈直到天亮
We sat and talked until it was light
他没有回家
He never went home
-你们一直谈到天亮吗? -我们不断谈话
-You sat and talked until it was light? -We sat and talked, Addison
我要整理他的剧本合约
I want a run-of-the-play contract
像你这种人真是空前绝后
There never was, and there never will be, another like you
说句祝福话,什么都行
Well, say something Anything
恭喜!太棒!干得好!
Congratulations Skål Good work, Eve
-你把我当成什么了?
What do you take me for?
-我不知道,但你很有份量
I don't know that I "take you" for anything
可能吗?你竟用这种落伍的
Is it possible that you've confused me
小孩游戏技俩想来困惑我
with those backward children you've played tricks on?
对我跟对他们没二样
That you have the same contempt for me as for them?
我知道你话中有特别的意义 但我不明白是什么?
I'm sure you mean something, but I don't know what
看清楚,伊芙 这次你死定了
Look closely, Eve It's time you did
我是艾德生 杜维特 可不是你手中玩弄的傻瓜
I am Addison DeWitt I'm nobody's fool, least of all yours
-我从没有那种念头 -你有而且你仍然是
-I never intended you to be -Yes, you did, and you still do
-我还是不明白你在说什么 -现在我想午睡,重要的是
I don't know what you mean But I want to take my nap It's important
-现在重要的是我们谈一谈 -杀手对杀手 -冠军对冠军
-It's important that we talk, killer to killer -Champion to champion
在我眼里你不算冠军 你太不入流了
Not with me, you're no champion You're stepping up
艾德生,请你坦白说清楚
Please say what you have to say, plainly and distinctly,
然后出去,我想午睡
and then let me take my nap
很好,坦白而清楚 但没那必要 你跟我一样明白我要说的话
Very well Although it's unnecessary, because you know what I'm going to say
罗维可能会离开凯伦 但绝不是为了你
Lloyd may leave Karen, but he will not leave Karen for you
你这话是什么意思? 说得更坦白,更清楚点
-What do you mean by that? -More plainly and more distinctly?
我没到新天堂去看戏 或讨论你的梦想
I have not come to New Haven to see the play, discuss your dreams,
或从耶鲁墙上拉下长春藤
or pull the ivy from the walls of Yale
我是来告诉你不能嫁给罗维 或其他人
I came to tell you that you will not marry Lloyd, or anyone else,
因为我不允许
because I will not permit it
这跟你有何关? 一切都有关
-What have you got to do with it? -Everything
因为今晚之后 你将属于我
Because after tonight you will belong to me
属于…你?
Belong? To you?
-我不相信我的耳朵
I can't believe my ears
-成年人的陈腐之言
A dull cliché
属于你
"Belong" to you?
听来多邪恶 好像中古世纪的话
That sounds medieval Something out of an old melodrama
它比历史还老20年
So does the history of the world for the past 20 years
你的反应令我生气
I don't enjoy putting it this bluntly
坦白说我希望你会了解 并视为当然,我和你是一对
I'd hoped that you would have taken it for granted that you and I
视为理所当然?
"Taken it for granted?"
我俩?哈!
"That you and I ?"
牢牢记住只要你活着一天 绝不要嘲笑我
Now remember, as long as you live, never to laugh at me
你可嘲笑任何人或任何事 但绝不能笑我
At anything or anyone else, but never at me
-滚出去 -你这么做太冲动
-Get out -You're too short for that gesture
再说你这样太冒险了
Besides, it went out with Mrs Fiske
若你不滚,我就叫人 把你丢出去
Then if you won't get out, I'll have you thrown out
别拿电话!别去碰
Don't pick up that phone Don't even touch it
有件事会使你乖乖听我的
Something told you to do what I said, didn't it?
那种直觉值得几百万 是你买不到的,伊芙
That instinct is worth millions You can't buy it, Eve Cherish it
好好谈吧!我们放下武装 彼此放松心情
When that alarm goes off, go to your battle stations
现在开始,你名字不叫伊芙.哈林顿 而是叫葛芙 芬斯基
To begin with, your name is not Eve Harrington It's Gertrude Slescynski
那又怎么样?
What of it?
事实上你父母很穷 他们还活着
True, your parents were poor, and still are
他们想知道你现在如何? 在何处?
They would like to know how you are
-他们三年来没有你音讯了
They haven't heard from you for three years
-那又如何?
What of it?
这件事你看如何
A matter of opinion, granted
你在布威尔工作那是事实
It's also true you worked in a brewery
但你在布威尔的生活 显然不是你所描述的那样
But life there was not as dull as you pictured it
事实上你是老板娘 请侦探来跟踪的对象
It got less and less dull, until your boss's wife had your boss followed by detectives
她从没证明过任何事 -但花了五百块叫你离镇
-She never proved a thing! -But the $500 you got to get out of town
打发你来纽约,不是吗?
brought you straight to New York, didn't it?
付五百块打发你到纽约 对不对?
That $500 brought you straight to New York
他是个骗子,骗子!
She was a liar She was a liar!
回答我的问题 他是不是付你钱叫你离镇?
Answer my question Weren't you paid to get out of town?
根本没有艾迪,没有飞行员 你没结过婚
There was no Eddie, no pilot You've never been married
那位女人深爱的死亡英雄
That was not only a lie, it was an insult to dead heroes
不仅是欺骗而且是侮辱
and the women who loved them
旧金山根本没有舒伯特戏院 你也从未到过旧金山
San Francisco has no Shubert Theatre You've never been to San Francisco
这是个愚笨的说谎者 很容易被看穿,那不是你
That was a stupid lie, easy to expose, not worthy of you
我当时一定得见到玛歌呀!
I had to get in to meet Margo
我总得说些话,变成某人 让她喜欢我
I had to say something, be somebody Make her like me!
她真的很喜欢你,帮助你 信任你
She did like you She helped and trusted you
你却忘恩负义 -这不是事实
-You repaid her by trying to win Bill -That's not true!
-我在场 我看到你,如何伤害她
I was there I saw you and heard you through the dressing-room door
你利用我的名字和专栏 来威胁凯伦 获得蔻拉那角色
You used my name to blackmail Karen into getting you the part of Cora
这件事你骗了我 不!不!
-You lied to me about it -No!
我又不是三小时前 才开始和凯伦吃午饭
I had lunch with Karen not three hours ago
从她说的话,我了解真相 比她所知的还多
As always with women who try to find out things, she told more than she learnt
现在你又想改口,
Now do you want to change your story
前晚 罗维在你门口向你求婚吗?
about Lloyd beating at your door that night?
拜托!求求你!
Please, please
你这种行为真叫人震惊
That I should want you at all suddenly strikes me as the height of improbability
应该让你自生自灭的
But that in itself is probably the reason
大概是起了恻隐之心吧! 伊芙,你我都不是正经人物 这点我们是相同的
You're an improbable person, Eve, and so am I We have that in common
而且都轻视人性 无法爱人或被爱
Also a contempt for humanity, an inability to love and be loved
还有永不知足的野心和才气
Insatiable ambition and talent
我们应彼此互属对方 你在听我说吗?
We deserve each other Are you listening to me?
出声啊! 是的,我在听
-Then say so -Yes, Addison
你也明白且同意 你完全属于我吧?
And you realize and you agree how completely you belong to me?
是的!
Yes, Addison
那就去午睡,祝你今晚好运
Then take your nap, and good luck for tonight
今晚我不能表演
I won't play tonight
我办不到,不可能的 我无法再演下去
I couldn't Not possibly I couldn't go on
不能再演下去? 你的生命都献给表演了
"Couldn't go on"? You'll give the performance of your life
于是她将生命都献给了表演
(Addison) And she gave the performance of her life
那一晚是值得回忆的
And it was a night to remember, that night
莎拉奖的诸位高贵委员
Honored members of the Sarah Siddons Society,
诸位贵宾,女士先生们
distinguished guests, ladies and gentlemen
我应该说些什么呢?
What is there for me to say?
所有名言绢语都有人说过
Everything wise and witty has long since been said
他们比我更有智慧才气
by minds more mature and talents far greater than mine
如果要我也同样来谢谢你们 那就不必了
For me to thank you as equals would be presumptuous
我只不过是戏剧中的学徒
I am an apprentice in the theatre,
要跟诸位学习的地方还很多
and have much to learn from all of you
我只想说我既高兴又骄傲
Let me say only that I am proud and happy,
当我论及这祟高的荣耀
and that I regard this great honor
我的成就在世上并不足为道
not so much as an award for what I have achieved,
而是面对将来我尚未达成的
but as a standard to hold against what I have yet to accomplish
再说我这次的得奖 我只是小小一部份
And, further, that I regard it as bestowed upon me only in part
最大荣耀应属于戏剧界朋友
The larger share belongs to my friends in the theatre,
及戏剧的本身
and to the theatre itself
它给了我所有的
which has given me all I have
凭良心说 这成果该归功于你们
In good conscience, I must give credit where credit is due
感谢麦斯 法宾,亲爱的麦斯
To Max Fabian Dear Max
亲爱的,富感情,慷慨 又勇敢的麦斯 法宾
Dear sentimental, generous, courageous Max Fabian,
他给了无名气,没有经验 的业余演员一个机会
who took a chance on an unknown, untried amateur
感谢我戏剧界第一个朋友
To my first friend in the theatre,
她的仁慈和善意 我将永志难忘
whose kindness and graciousness I shall never forget,
凯伦 罗维夫人
Karen Mrs Lloyd Richards
是凯伦带我去见一个 我永远喜爱的明星
It was Karen who first brought me to one whom I'd always idolized,
一个成为我的恩人 才有今日的获奖
one who became my benefactress and champion
伟大的女演员 以及伟大的女人
A great actress and a great woman,
玛歌.嘉琳
Margo Channing
感谢我的导演
To my director,
他总是要求我很高
who demanded always a little more than my talent could provide,
但他却耐心地教导我
but who taught me patiently and well,
比尔 辛普生
Bill Sampson
还有一位,没有他伟大的剧本
And one without whose great play and faith in me,
就没有今晚的我
this night could never have been
我该如何报答罗维 瑞奇呢
How can I repay Lloyd Richards?
叫我该如何报答其它的人呢
How can I repay the many others,
实在太多,我无法一一指名
so many, I couldn't possibly name them all,
他们的协助,指导和忠告
whose help, guidance, and advice
让今晚成为我生命中 最快乐的一晚,或许吧
have made this, the happiest night of my life, possible
虽然我将在下星期 到好莱坞拍片
Although I am going to Hollywood next week to make a film,
千万别认为我会离开你们
do not think for a moment that I am leaving you
我怎么能呢?
How could I?
我的心在此,在剧场中
My heart is here in the theatre,
但是离开你们的心 三千哩是太远了
and 3,000 miles are too far to be away from one's heart
我会尽快回来相聚
I'll be back to claim it, and soon
当然是如果你们要我回来
That is, if you want me back
各位!晚安!
Good night to you all, and to all, a good night
不管如何,这应该归功于你,达令
For services rendered beyond whatever it is of duty, darling
快走吧!我是主人 我得在我的宾客尿裤子前 赶到家才行的
Come on, I'm the host I got to get home before my guests start stealing the liquor
-恭喜!伊芙 -凯伦,谢谢你
-Congratulations, Eve -Thank you, Karen
-恭喜你!哈林顿小姐 -非常感谢!
-Congratulations, Miss Harrington -Oh, thank you so much
讲得真好! -不过我不会担心你的心
Nice speech, Eve But I wouldn't worry too much about your heart
你可把奖座跟你心摆在一起
You can always put that award where your heart ought to be
我想酒大概都没剩吧!
I don't suppose there's a drink left?
-麦斯待会要开个酒会 -我不会去的
-You can have one at Max's -I don't think I'm going
-为什么呢? -因为我不想
-Why not? -Because I don't want to
-我真为你感到高兴,伊芙 -非常感谢
-I'm so happy for you, Eve -Thank you so much
麦斯恐怕会很麻烦的
Max has gone to a lot of trouble
这是为你的胜利所开的派对
This is going to be an elaborate party and it's for you
不,他不是,是为了这个
No, it isn't It's for this
-是同样的东西,不是吗? -正是!
-It's the same thing, isn't it? -Exactly
-拿这个代替我去参加派对好了
Here, take it to the party instead of me
-你太孩子气了!
You're being very childish
-我累了,想回家 -很好 我送你回家
-I'm tired I want to go home -Very well I'll drop you off
我自己去参加宴会
I shall go to the party alone I have no intention of missing it
-你是谁? -哈林顿小姐
-Who are you? -Miss Harrington
-你在这做什么? 我大概是睡着了
-What are you doing here? -I I guess I fell asleep
千万别叫人逮捕我! 求求你,我并没偷东西 你可以搜我身
Please don't have me arrested I didn't steal anything You can search me
你怎么进来的? 我来到外面的大厅 直到女佣来清理你的床
-How did you get in here? -I hid outside till the maid came in
她大概忘了什么又走回来 走时,忘了关上门
She went out to get something and left the door open
我溜进来,直到她清理完毕 我只是四处看看
I sneaked in and hid till she'd finished Then I just looked around
怕引起注意,把灯全关了
I was afraid someone would notice the lights were on, so I turned them off
然后我大概就睡着了 -你只是四处看看?
-Then I guess I fell asleep -You were just looking around?
-就只这样 -为什么?
-That's all -What for?
-你大概不会相信我的 -大概不会
-You probably won't believe me -Probably not
-是关于我的报导 -什么报导?对谁的报导?
-It was for my report -What report? To whom?
关于你的起居 你穿什么样的衣服
About how you live, what kind of clothes you wear,
香水,书籍,这类的事
what kind of perfume and books, things like that
你晓得你拥有许多高中 女学生组成的影友会
You know the Eve Harrington Club that they have in most girls' high schools?
我听说过 我是第一位发起人
-I've heard of them -Ours was one of the first, Erasmus Hall
影友会的主席 -俄伦斯弗高中 -在布鲁克林区是吧!
-I'm the president -Erasmus Hall That's in Brooklyn, isn't it?
还有许多女影星来自 布鲁克林区 有芭芭拉史丹妃,苏珊海华
Lots of actresses come from Brooklyn Barbara Stanwyck and Susan Hayward
当然她们只是电影明星
Of course, they're just movie stars
你要去好莱坞,是吗?
You're going to Hollywood, aren't you?
是的
Mm-hm
看你收拾的行李 一定是要待很久啰!
From the trunks you're packing, you must be going to stay a long time
或许吧!
I might
那些泼出来的饮料 会弄坏你的地毯
That spilled drink's gonna ruin your carpet
明早再清理!
Maid'll fix it in the morning
-我来清理吧! -别麻烦了
-I'll just clean up the mess -Don't bother
-你如何从布鲁克林区来到这? -地铁
-How'd you get up here from Brooklyn? -Subway
要多久?
How long does it take?
不太一定,一个多小时吧!
With changing and everything, a little over an hour
够久了,你到家会很晚
It's after one now You won't get home till all hours
我不在乎回不了家
I don't care if I never get home
门铃!
That's the door
你休息吧!我去开门
You rest I'll get it
哈啰!你是谁?
Hello Who are you?
哈小姐在休息,杜维特先生 她要我过来看看是谁?
Miss Harrington's resting, Mr DeWitt She asked me to see who it is
那我就不吵她了
Well, we won't disturb her rest
哈小姐将奖座遗留在计程车上 你拿给她,好吗?
It seems Miss Harrington left her award in the taxi cab Will you give it to her?
告诉我你怎么知道我名字?
Tell me, how did you know my name?
那是个很有名的名字 杜维特先生
It's a very famous name, Mr DeWitt
那你叫什么? -菲比
-And what's your name? -Phoebe
我自称是菲比
-Phoebe? -I call myself Phoebe
有何不可呢?
And why not?
菲比,告诉我 你希不希望将来自己能有 一座这样的奖杯?
Tell me, Phoebe, do you want someday to have an award like that of your own?
超过世界上的任何东西 那你得问哈小姐怎么得到的?
-More than anything else in the world -Then ask Miss Harrington how to get one
哈小姐,她一清二楚
Miss Harrington knows all about it
是谁呀!
(Eve) Who was it?
哈小姐,是计程车司机
Just a taxi driver, Miss Harrington
你把奖杯留在车上 他送回来了
You left your award in his cab, and he brought it back
帮我放到行李箱上,好吗? 我要打包
(Eve) Put it on one of the trunks, will you? I wanna pack it
没问题,哈小姐
Sure, Miss Harrington